<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The imperious brother· Dedicated to the Countess of Strafford.</title>
            <title>Sucessos y prodigias de amor. Book 3. English</title>
            <author>Pérez de Montalván, Juan, 1602-1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1469aA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1569_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203136</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863205</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863205</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170098</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170098)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 198:E1569[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The imperious brother· Dedicated to the Countess of Strafford.</title>
                  <title>Sucessos y prodigias de amor. Book 3. English</title>
                  <author>Pérez de Montalván, Juan, 1602-1638.</author>
                  <author>Phillips, Edward, 1630-1696?</author>
                  <author>Pérez de Montalván, Juan, 1602-1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 84, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for Nath. Brook, at the Angel in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of book 3 of: Pérez de Montalván, Juan.  Sucessos y prodigias de amor.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: E.P. [i.e. Edward Phillips].</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Includes The imperious brother only.</note>
                  <note>With two final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy title page: "feb: 12"; the second 6 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "5".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:170098:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IMPERIOUS BROTHER.</p>
            <p>Dedicated to the COUNTESS OF <hi>STRAFFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>Nath. Brook,</hi> at the Angel in Cornhil, 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170098:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170098:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, THE COUNTESS OF <hi>STRAFFORD.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Boldneſs which I preſume in ſuffring this little Volume to make its Humble Addreſs to your Honours fair Hands, is ſo great, that I ſhould deſpair of ever finding Pardon,
<pb facs="tcp:170098:3"/>were it not that the Vertuous <hi>Stella,</hi> a Lady, both Noble in Extraction, and in the Luſtre of her Beauty and Soul, yet in all theſe, infinitely inferiour to your Honour, lies proſtrate at your Feet, imploring a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs for this Preſumption; and to make it known, That ſhe owes her Deſcription to a more Noble Author; ſince all the Glory I pretend to, is, to have the Honour of Preſenting Her to You in the Engliſh Dreſs: Yet when I conſider, that among the Old Greeks, the meaneſt Off'rings, which with a pure Heart they Conſecrated to the Temples of their Divinities,
<pb facs="tcp:170098:3"/>found no leſs favourable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, than thoſe Statues and Veſſels of maſſy Gold, which were Offer'd by that <hi>Lydian</hi> Monarch, the Envie of his Age for Riches, unto the Temple of <hi>Jupiter Hammon,</hi> when his Thoughts had devour'd all <hi>Aſia</hi> with his Numerous Army: I am the more For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified in the Confidence of this Addreſs; it being made unto a Greatneſs, equal to thoſe who have been eſteemed Deities; and to a Goodneſs, incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly more Obliging: Eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly having aſſum'd the Confidence to Dedicate the <hi>Illuſtrious Shepherdeſs</hi> to your Noble
<pb facs="tcp:170098:4"/>Siſter, the Marchioneſs of <hi>Dorcheſter;</hi> to whom the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is the ſame in Merit as in Nature; both being Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to that moſt honour'd Lady, who is known to the World as much by the Greatneſs of Her Vertues, as Her Quality. It had been the higheſt of Errors to have Preſented this to Any, but Your Self, whoſe Illuſtrious Affiances, ſince I have had the happy occaſion to mention, I ought not to forget to pay a juſt Adoration unto the Memory of that Renowned Lord, whoſe High Prudence and Heroick Magnanimity ſtill Survive in the perfect Image of his Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,
<pb facs="tcp:170098:4"/>your Noble Husband. And, Madam, I am bold to Affirm, That <hi>Montalvan</hi> Himſelf, the Grandeur of whoſe Air and Spirit in all his Writings, have render'd him an Admiration to all men that have been ſo fortunate as to reade Him, would, had he had the like Opportunity, have thrown himſelf, and all his Works, at your Feet, with a Devotion as equal to that wherewith the Famous <hi>Scu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dery</hi> Preſented his <hi>Cyrus</hi> to the Dutcheſs of <hi>Longevile,</hi> as all thoſe Glories and Tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies of Mind and Body, which he Attributes to that
<pb facs="tcp:170098:5"/>Great Princeſs, are equall'd, if not excell'd by thoſe Divine Rays of Vertue which Crown you with unſpeakable Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: And it is but juſt, that this Piece, which ſmall as it is, hath not many fewer Examples of Vertue and Heroick Actions in it, than the moſt Voluminous Romance containeth, ſhould be Conſecrated to a Perſonage, who alone, Comprizeth all that's Great and Noble in the World: But, Conſidering how ſmall the Advantages are which this Verſion hath Contributed to it, and that what there is of Handſom in it, it Derives from the Original; to hope, that an
<pb facs="tcp:170098:5"/>Eſſay ſo little Worth, coming from a Perſon leſs worthy, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhin'd and Eclips'd by ſo many nobler Productions, ſhould finde an Acceptance equal with the Devotion wherewith it is Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, were an Arrogance as Great as the Perſon againſt whom it is Preſum'd. But on the other-ſide, not to repoſe a Confidence on thoſe Extenſive and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Civilities which you equally diſtribute to all men, were to call in queſtion that high Complaiſance, that generous mildneſs of Nature which hath gain'd you ſo large an Empire over the Spirits of all the <hi>Vertuoſi;</hi> whenas the Sun,
<pb facs="tcp:170098:6"/>your Emulatour, in the large diffuſion of his Favours indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently upon all Objects, ſhines as well upon the ignobleſt Weed, as on the moſt radiant Flower: at leaſtwiſe I may Hope, That <hi>Stella</hi> being of a middle Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, between your heighth of Glory and my Imperfections, as the Moon is between the purity of the Sun, and the groſſeneſs of the Earth, may receive the light of your Rays, and reflect it back upon this Humble Addreſs: for a meaner Excellency, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the preſence of Deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſet it off, would yet enjoy a conſiderable Felicity, if it ſhould be thought to deſerve the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:170098:6"/>of being a Foil to your more exalted Brightneſs: And per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, there are in <hi>Stella</hi> ſuch Advantages, as may allow her a pretenſion to that Honour, and admit her to wait upon your Triumphal Chariot; an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, in which ſhe will ſhine more gloriouſly than any of thoſe bright Creatures, whoſe Name ſhe bears, do in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens: and whatever Defects ſhe may be thought culpable of, I am perſwaded they are neither ſo Many, nor ſo Great, but that they may be capable to Merit your Condeſcention and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs; and thereby Confirm you Eminent, by the Diſcovery of
<pb facs="tcp:170098:7"/>one Vertue more, for whom all Noble Attributes are reſerv'd, of which there can be none Greater than that of your Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in cheriſhing a Vertue which Offers her ſelf up to your Service with ſo perfect and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous a Reſignation: And it is with the ſame Devotion to your Service, though far leſs preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Merit, that I Paſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately Aſpire to be Admitted into the Glorious Quality of being,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>MADAM, Your Honours moſt Humble, moſt Faithful, and moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>E. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170098:7"/>
            <head>The Illuſtrious SHEPHERDESS.</head>
            <p>The Imperious BROTHER.</p>
            <p>Written originally in Spaniſh:</p>
            <p>Now made ENGLISH, And Dedicated to the MARCHIONESS Of <hi>DORCHESTER,</hi> And the COUNTESS Of <hi>STRAFFORD,</hi> BY <hi>E. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>Nath. Brook,</hi> at the Angel in Cornhil. 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170098:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170098:8"/>
            <head>The Imperious <hi>BROTHER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N <hi>Sevil,</hi> a place both otherwiſe famous, and for being the capital Citie of <hi>Andaluzia,</hi> was born <hi>Carlo</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſon of Count <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratia,</hi> who for his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous qualittes was ſo well belov'd, that all that knew him were afflicted that he was not the chief Heir of his fathers e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. He was in his deportment gentile and pleaſing; of a comely &amp; graceful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; in his apparel not exceeding the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration that became a younger brother: but that which was chiefly commendable, he was of a clear and candid Judgment; a gift which doth not always ſpeak men fortunate. His Brother, whole name was <hi>Alfredo,</hi> though ſuperiout in years, yet in vertues far inferiour, by the death of his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170098:9"/>father became poſſeſs'd of all his honor'd Titles and great Poſſeſſions; his right pre-exiſting above his brother <hi>Carlo</hi>'s by the priviledge onely of one years Seniori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: He was more envious than for one of his quality might ſeem poſſible; proud, and above ſufferance imperious: and in ſo deſpightful and haughty a manner trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he <hi>Carlo,</hi> as that he might well have been thought rather his utter enemy, then his brother. If any thing may be ſaid in favour of <hi>Alfredo,</hi> it is this; That ſince he would needs be envious, his Envie could not have ſound a nobler object. O powerful Diſeaſe! how generally doſt thou reign over the whole world, and how ſtrangely infeſt all ſorts and degrees of men! thou not onely frequenteſt Courts, Palaces, Univerſities, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Societies themſelves; but even tainteſt the blood of perſons moſt neerly related. But whereas <hi>Alfredo</hi> was of ſo uncontrol'd a power, ſo reſpected and ſo fear'd of all; what reaſon had he to bear ſo great an envie toward one ſo curb'd and depreſs'd, that there ſeemed no great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between him and one of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants? There needs no other anſwer, but that famous ſaying of an ancient Author: <hi>The Envious man hates all: his Inferiours,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170098:9"/>becauſe they do not equal him; his Equals, becauſe they do not exceed him; his Superiours, becauſe they are above him:</hi> ſo that neither brothers nor deareſt friends are exempted from his malice. It was Envie which put ſo great a difference between the two Romane twins, who had the ſelf-ſame Cradle upon the banks of <hi>Tyber,</hi> and the ſelf-ſame Couch in the Hoſtile field that <hi>Romulus,</hi> to aſſume the whole Empire to himſelf, gave licenſe to the murthering of his brother <hi>Remus:</hi> It was Envie which ſo diſ-united the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of powerful <hi>Mithridates</hi> from his brother, that <hi>Mithridates,</hi> to enlarge his power and dominion, commanded his brother to be publikely beheaded. To conclude, where this Monſter ruleth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means, nor honours, nor even life it ſelf, can promiſe any to themſelves ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Carlo,</hi> that he might ſet himſelf to reſiſt the diſcourteſies of Fortune, and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend any longer upon his brothers cold courteſies, he reſolves to engage himſelf in the love of ſome fair and rich Lady of that Citie, whoſe portion might diſ-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thral him from that ſervile eſtate which he liv'd in under his brothers tyranny. But among all the Illuſtrious Dames which that famous place afforded, (and it afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not a few) he thought none more fair,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170098:10"/>and there was none more rich, than a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy whoſe name was <hi>Donna Stella,</hi> whoſe father was of the nobleſt and wealthieſt Gentlemen of the Citie, having acquir'd a great eſtate in the <hi>Indies.</hi> This <hi>Stella</hi> was doubly fair, as being both fair and rich: both theſe reſpects make <hi>Carlo</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be her ſervant; both theſe reſpects render <hi>Stello</hi> worthy of his ſervice: but as yet he is reſolv'd to communicate his degſines to no body but his own thoughts. There is nothing that abateth the courage of Lovers more then Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; nothing that more reſtraineth them from revealing the ſecrets of their minds. If the riches of <hi>Stella</hi> mov'd him at firſt to ſeek her love, no leſs powerful with him is her beauty now, to perſwade him to perſevere in that minde: but the means and oportunity of diſcovering his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful flames, and preferring his amorous ſuit to her, were denied him by the male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence of his ſtars. He knew he was not able to promote his deſigne, nor have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to his Miſtreſs, without employing the induſtry and fidelity of ſome of her ſervants: and to have made uſe of their aſſiſtance, without the demonſtration of his own liberality, would have been a great diſhonour to him, not having where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170098:10"/>to reward them according to the greatneſs of his Generoſity and Birth, as being Brother to him who was abſolute Lord of the whole Country. To prove ungrateful, the generouſneſs of his minde made him ſcorn; to appear co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ferable, and in want, the greatneſs of his ſpirit made him diſdain: therefore the language of his eyes only had liberty to expreſs that which his tongue was conſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal. The day came nor more certainly, then he was certain to diſpoſe of himſelf in ſome ſecret Walk neer the back part of her houſe; that if at any time ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me forth that way, he might obtain his wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſight: and there paſs'd not a night, wherein he did not duely walk by the door of her houſe; that at leaſt if he might not be ſo happie as to enjoy her ſight, he might in ſome ſort pleaſe himſelf with ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place made happie by her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. But when he conſider'd with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf what an airy contentment he now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd, and that time was trifl'd away, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d his loves labour loſt, while his affections were kept unreveal'd from her who was the Miſtreſs of his affections; and that he had ſmall reaſon to expect favours from her, who ſcarce knew him, much leſs knew him to be her ſervant; he ſaw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170098:11"/>conſtrain'd (for want of other means) to caſt himſelf upon the courteſie of his diſcourteous Brother, and to impart thoſe counſels to him, which he had purpos'd to lock up in the moſt ſecret <hi>Arcanum</hi> of his breſt; preſuming he ſhould come off with the more credit, and his addreſs to his Miſtreſs finde greater acceptance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back'd by his brothers authority; whom although he knew not to ſtand ſo well-affected to him or his proceedings, yet he aſſur'd himſelf that he might haply be led to it, if not by any other reſpect, yet at leaſt by a willingneſs to be rid of his company he ſo little car'd for, and to be freed from the charge he was at in maintaining him; with this aſſurance, he repairs to <hi>Alfredo,</hi> repreſents to him the exquiſiteneſs of <hi>Stella</hi>'s beauty, and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually ſets forth with what paſſionate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires her beauty had enflam'd him, and how extremely it perplex'd him not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that which he ſo infinitely deſir'd. His Brother outwardly commended his diſcreet choice, inwardly maligned it; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to further him in it what he might, intended nothing leſs: for having conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd well the excellent feature and the rare endowments of <hi>Stella,</hi> he purpos'd to obtain her for himſelf; nor did he ſeek
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170098:11"/>her more for his own love and her deſerts ſake, then out of a deſire to deprive his brother of that contentment and felicity he aim'd at; ſo great was his envie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him: whoſe mean and lowe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if it were ſo much the object of his envie; how much more would he have been envi'd, being advanc'd to a contented and proſperous eſtate, wherein he ſhould not any longer have ſtood in need of him! He was not, in times paſt, ſo much not his friend, as now he is reſolv'd to become his mortal adverſary: ſo that, making his brothers deſires the promoters of his own deſigne, he often frequented the houſe of <hi>Stella</hi>'s father, and, after a few viſits, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd to him his minde. No marvel if the old man willingly conſented; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that to accept of the Counts profer, imported him no leſs then the marrying of his daughter to the greateſt Fortune in that Country. In all haſte, he goes to <hi>Stella,</hi> and tells her the happie news: who grown to womans eſtate, and thinking the time long till ſhe were married, embrac'd the motion with much gladneſs. <hi>Carlo</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his brother to be much at the houſe of <hi>Stella</hi>'s father, reſted ſecure of his good ſucceſs. He whoſe minde is free from traiterous intentions, is leaſt apt to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170098:12"/>ſuſpect others for being guilty of the like, <hi>Stella,</hi> by ſome means or other, became ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with <hi>Carlo</hi>'s affection to her; which could not finde any place in her heart, being prepoſſeſt already by that of <hi>Alfredo.</hi> And there wanted not thoſe, on the other ſide, who inform'd <hi>Carle</hi> of his brothers proceedings toward him; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading him from continuing any longer a ſervant to her, for that ſhe was extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incens'd againſt him, both for his bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in aſpiring to her favours, which were elſewhere beſtow'd; and for his raſhneſs, to ſtand in competition with his brothers Authority in ſo high a nature, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his Rival. In this manner did the two Brothers proſecute the ſame deſigne; but with far different ſucceſs: <hi>Carlo</hi>'s love was hindered by the fraud of <hi>Alfredo; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fredo</hi>'s ſeconded by the favour of <hi>Stella.</hi> Notwithſtanding <hi>Carlo,</hi> ſeeing himſelf thus ſlighted, was reſolved not ſo eaſily to take a repulſe from one whom he never talk'd with; but rather to try if by ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with her, who was the cauſe of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent flames, he could prevail with her to know what ſhould be the cauſe of her diſdain. This reſolution of his was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by an accident no leſs fortunate than unexpected; he having long, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170098:12"/>with much impatience awaited the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of night, at length that ſilent ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon came, wherein darkneſs and ſolitude had given truce to the buſie motions and labours of men, and kept the inquiſitive neighbours from ſtirring abroad to his hinderance; when <hi>Carlo,</hi> more curious then prudent, haſtes toward the Manſion of his Beloved, whom to his joy he found ſtanding in a Balcone, in expectation of <hi>Alfredo</hi>'s coming: for ſeeing him reſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bent to be her Spouſe, ſhe long'd to have conference with him firſt, without any other witneſs than the ſtill ſilence of night, that ſhe might make trial whether his wit and underſtanding were correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the properneſs of his perſon, and the greatneſs of his eſtate: having abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely concluded with her ſelf, that if he prov'd any way defective of judgement, ſhe would rather chuſe to want the pomp and ſplendour which his alliance would bring her, then to tie her ſelf to the tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of leading her whole life with ſuch a one, whom folly and ſimplicity ſhould make unfit to be convers'd with. <hi>Carlo</hi> imputed it to the goodneſs of his ſtars, that he had lighted upon an occaſion ſo much according to his deſire, ſo much beyond his hopes; and ſo drew neer unto
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170098:13"/>her: and ſhe imagining nothing more, than that it was the Count himſelf, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it had been agreed between them the night before, to meet in this place, and at the very ſame hour) receiv'd him with more obliging expreſſions then he had reaſon or hopes to expect: and after ſhe had affirm'd to him her great deſire to ſpeak with him, ſhe entertain'd him with the ſubtil'ſt and moſt complemental diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe (for ſhe was not altogether void of Eloquence) that her womans wit could furniſh her withal; that the acuteneſs of his wit and underſtanding might be made to appear and he reply'd in terms ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous and diſcreet, that <hi>Stella</hi> render'd Heaven thanks for her happie fortune, in having obtain'd a ſervant ſo compleat and to her minde, that her own fancie could not have depainted forth a nobler. Thus were they both deluded, both favour'd by each other. <hi>Stella</hi> perſwading her ſelf that <hi>Alfredo,</hi> and no other man in the world, was to be poſſeſſor of her beauty, <hi>That pleaſure,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>Alfredo, that you have done me, in coming ſo alone to viſit me alone, at a time and place ſo lovely, is ſuch, that it ought not to be register'd in the roll of common courteſies. I have had a great deſire to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate unto you ſome particulars which have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170098:13"/>diſturb'd the tranquility of my minde: And although I would willingly have conceal'd this diſtaſte; yet becauſe it is a kinde of treaſon in the Will, to bury in ſilence thoſe things which ought to be reveal'd, I ſhould make my ſelf guilty of this crime, if I ſhould hide this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from you, which it imports you ſo much to know. Carlo</hi> exceedingly amaz'd to ſee that he ſhould be ſo much not diſeern'd by <hi>Stella</hi> as to be taken by her for <hi>Alfredo,</hi> diſſembled as much as in him lay, the trouble and confuſion of his thoughts; and recollecting himſelf, turns to his beloved Enemy, to hear what ſhe had far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſay; who thus went on: <hi>You are to know</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>that your Brother</hi> Carlo, <hi>who in the opinion of moſt is held for diſcreet and vertuous, is ſo diſcourteous to my Honor, ſo trayterous to your Love, that having fixed his affections on me, he not conſidering that I was born to be wholly yours, boldly promiſeth to himſelf a poſsibility of triumphing over the conqueſt of my Will: how audacious and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate a beſieger of my Chaſtity he is, theſe Walls, which at all hours he haunts, can teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie; inſomuch that I have ſome reaſon to be afraid, leſt at this very moment of time, that we are now talking together, he ſhould be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hearing of us. I had certainly conceal'd from you this extravagancy of his, had not this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170098:14"/>conſideration mov'd me to be willing rather to let you underſtand it from me than any body elſe, that, if haply you may hereafter hear from the hand of any body beſide, this thing ſo tending to your diſhonor, you may aſſure your ſelf it was not my beauty, but his want of wiſdom, which prompted him to ſo inconſider ate an attempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No wonder if <hi>Carlo</hi> with the utmoſt of his diſcretion had enough to do to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs his outragious paſſions, which through the anguiſh of his mind, were ready to burſt forth into vehement out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries; on the one ſide he ſaw himſelf diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd by her whom he moſt admir'd, on the other ſide injur'd by him of whom it was impoſſible for him to take revenge: the rigour and neglect of <hi>Stella</hi> pierc'd him deeply to the heart, and as deeply did he reſent the blows of adverſe Fortune, which ſo apparently perſecuted him, but that which moſt of all afflicted him, was, To have a Brother of ſo perfideous a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that having been intreated with ſo much ſubmiſſion, ſuch a deluge of tears, to aſſiſt him in obtaining the reward of his faithful and long-languiſhing deſires, had not only not effected it, but with a moſt ignoble fraud, ſought himſelf to reap that fruit which for ſo many days his hopes had husbanded. <hi>Carlo</hi> was juſt about to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170098:14"/>frame an Anſwer to <hi>Stella,</hi> if he had not at that very inſtant been diſturb'd by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Man interpoſing himſelf between them; who told him, <hi>That this place which he poſſeſt, was by right anothers, and therefore deſired him preſentty to avoid it. Stella</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him that came laſt to be <hi>Carlo,</hi> was afraid, leſt if they had come to Swords-diſpute, the life of <hi>Alfredo</hi> would have been in danger. But <hi>Carlo</hi> leſs diſmaid than glad at this preſent occaſion, judg'd it now a fit time to eaſe his big ſtomack of that great indignation wherewith it ſwel'd by reaſon of the former injury offer'd him, by taking revenge of this preſent affront; and either not thinking him that ſurpriz'd him to be his Brother, or thinking if it were he, to take a brave revenge of him for his treacherous dealing, he, with his rapier drawn, anſwer'd him in ſuch rugged tearms, that if <hi>Alfredo</hi> had not quickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, 'tis to be doubted, leſt he had ſtay'd to the hazard of his life. By this time the tumult was heard by ſome of <hi>Alfredo</hi>'s Attendants, that had ſtay'd a pretty way behinde; they coming neer, and knowing <hi>Carbo,</hi> admoniſh'd him by all means to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt from ſo unadviſed an Enterprize: ſo both parties retired, without ſo much as ſpeaking to each other, or giving any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170098:15"/>as for <hi>Alfredo,</hi> his pride was ſuch, he would give none; <hi>Carlo</hi> was ſo injur'd, he had no cauſe to give any.</p>
            <p>Poor deluded <hi>Stella</hi> remains all this while in great perplexity of minde; yet glad to ſee, that the courage of her ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Lover, was anſwerable to the preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy of his wit: ſo that whereas <hi>Carlo</hi> had been the Actor of ſo much Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, <hi>Alfredo</hi> uſurped the praiſe and honor. <hi>Carlo</hi> was he, that both by his Language and Valour raviſh'd the thoughts of <hi>Stella; Alfredo</hi> was the Man thought worthy of her Affection and care, triumphing in the atchievement of Actions which he could never own. <hi>Alfredo</hi> would no longer delay the execution of his Will, but went again the day following to <hi>Stella</hi>'s Father, to conſult farther with him about the Match: from whom he receiv'ed this comfortable Anſwer, <hi>That he might ſecurely build upon this aſſurance, that ſhe ſhould be his; and, that it might appear how much the good will he bore to his Daughter pleaſed him, he from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth gave him free leave to viſit her as often as he pleaſed.</hi> This permiſſion, which <hi>Alfredo</hi> eſteemed the greateſt of Favours, he ſoon made uſe of, and went forthwith to viſit <hi>Stella;</hi> who receiv'd him with a charming Modeſty, honouring him with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170098:15"/>thoſe gracious and rich Beams of Favour from her fair Eyes, that thoſe of far more merit than himſelf might have been proud of the like. They had not far entred into their Diſcourſe, which was of ſundry mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, before <hi>Alfredo,</hi> beſides that he betray'd much ignorance, utter'd ſo many unſavory and impertinent ſpeeches, that <hi>Stella</hi> quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerv'd neither his Behaviour nor his Wrds to be any way conſiſtent with that which ſhe had been Witneſs of the night before; and the thought of this, took ſo ſtrong an impreſſion in her minde, that in ſtead of reſolving him fully in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which he came about, ſhe earneſtly deſired of her Father to give her time to conſider of it, that ſhe might not raſhly enter into a condition which ſhe muſt be tied to all her life-time, without well conſidering beforehand what ſhe went about. <hi>Alfredo</hi> remained for the time pretty well ſatisfied, although not free from ſuſpicion, both becauſe he had ſeen <hi>Carlo</hi> with her the night before, and becauſe ſhe was doubtful in her Anſwers when he made the motion: nevertheleſs, relying upon the promiſe which her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had made him, he gave out, that within four dayes he was to be Married. This went for currant among credulous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170098:16"/>vulgar, who obſerving him often frequent that houſe, thought nothing able to reſiſt the power and will of ſo mighty a man. With what grief and amazement the Heart of <hi>Carlo</hi> was ſtruck when he heard this news, let him judge who hath loſt the chief joy of his life by ſo unjuſt a way. <hi>Carlo</hi> now expects no other than to ſee himſelf miſerable, than to ſee in the arms of his Adverſary, his lov'd <hi>Stella;</hi> yet <hi>Carlo</hi> ſtill loves, <hi>Carlo</hi> is ſtill diſcreet: can it poſſibly be, that he ſhould either love or be diſcreet, and not become fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick with grief, being ſo injuriouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of his hopes and deſires? Having oft revolved theſe things in his minde, at laſt he reaſon'd thus to himſelf, That if his Competitor, either a ſtranger or his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, had done this wrong, he ſhould not have had that cauſe to admire; but that his own Brother ſhould do him ſo great a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite both in his Content, his Credit, and his Honour, was a vexation ſo grievous to him, that although neceſſity forced him to undergo it, yet his ſtomack would not permit him to endure it. A thouſand times did he, incited with theſe injuries, vow to revenge himſelf; and at other times repented himſelf of his raſh Vow, not ſo much out of tenderneſs to his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170098:16"/>as for fear of offending <hi>Stella:</hi> but at length, ſeeing there were ſmall hopes left him of ever being able to prevent thoſe misfortunes which grew ſo faſt upon him, he pitch'd upon this, as the ſureſt courſe he could betake himſelf to; namely, for a while to ſhake hands with his native Country, thereby to try if while he chang'd his Climate, Fortune would ſmile upon him with a more propitious coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance: So putting himſelf into a Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary garb, he reſolv'd upon a voyage to <hi>Madrid,</hi> with an intention to procure Letters of recommendation from thence to <hi>Don Juan</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> who at that time govern'd the Low-Countries. <hi>Alfredo</hi> applauded his noble Reſolution; Saying, <hi>That it became men nobly born, to ſet upon the braveſt and higheſt Adventures, ſuch as might lead them to Fortunes, which (however de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni'd them by the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſimonie of their Fates) were yet moſt correſpondent to the greatneſs of their qualities:</hi> and readily furniſhed him with two thouſand Crowns, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h his promiſe to be Aſſiſtant to him upon all emergencies. <hi>Carlo</hi> reſted ſatisfied, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting himſelf with this thought. That whatever benefit he enjoy'd beſide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he ſhould at leaſt be freed from having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually before his eyes the object of his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170098:17"/>diſquiet, and that the large diſtance of place would ſeparate between him and thoſe inconveniences, which, remaining at home, he muſt have unavoidably run into: And when the time of his departure drew nigh, he us'd to come abroad in ſo brave an Equipage, that like the Sun under a Cloud, he appeared bright in the midſt of obſcurity; nor did he ſhew forth leſs gallantry than if he had liv'd in the height of Splendor and content. Thus being clad in sky colour'd Sattin (a true Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of the grief he ſuffered) edg'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with Gold, while the braveneſs of his Aſpect drew admiration from the peoples eyes, the croſſneſs of his Stars drew pity from their hearts. But he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, That to take his journey without firſt giving <hi>Stella</hi> a viſit, would be both a great diſcourteſie, and a thing apt to breed ſuſpition, he went to take leave of her, and to receive his diſpatch from her fair eyes; both that the memory of them might be the more freſh and preſent with him in his travels, and that their kind influence might be the more auſpicious to his enterprizes: he found her more ſad than ſhe was accuſtom'd to be, or than he imagin'd to have found her; yet he made no great wonder at it, becauſe he perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170098:17"/>himſelf for a certain, That this ſolitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs of hers was rather feigned, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſend him on his journey the more cheerful and contented, than any real ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row conceiv'd for his departure; ſo eaſie it is to ſhew favour to any, when we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine it is the laſt favour we ſhall need to ſhew them; but moſt certain it is, that <hi>Stella</hi> weighing with her ſelf the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing conditions of <hi>Alfredo,</hi> his mean wit, and his immeaſurable pride, was much troubled in her minde, that ſhe had ſo far imparted her favours towards him, as that ſhe was hardly able to recal them; being ſomwhat aſham'd to let her father now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand her diſaffection to him, to whom he knew ſhe had formerly expreſt ſo much good will; complaining much of her hard hap, for that ſhe had ſeen ſo much deſert in a man whom both her honour and her former choice conſtrain'd her to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpect. In the midſt of theſe troubles and doubts, ſo deep a melancholy poſſeſt her, that it caus'd admiration and pity in all that knew her and beheld her in that diſconſolate plight, which began to ſeize upon her from this very time that <hi>Carlo</hi> came to take his farewel of her: for care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly lifting up her eyes upon him, after ſhe had earneſtly view'd all his perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170098:18"/>his ſprightly carriage, his comely perſon, and the noble anger and diſdain he ſhew'd in accuſing the ſevere carriage of his Lordly Brother towards him; ſhe intreated the cauſe of this ſo ſuddenly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken journey. Whereunto, in brief and diſcreet terms, he reply'd, <hi>That in his own Country he perceiv'd himſelf ſo diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly entreated, as he could not with any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent or ſatisfaction to his mind remain at home, and therefore had bethought himſelf of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to try if by living in a place where he was leſs known, he ſhould be more reſpected. But the principal reaſon which incited him to this voluntary baniſhment was the fervent affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherewith he had devoted himſelf to a Lady of that City; whom yet he lov'd ſo warily, and with ſuch reſpect, that although for her ſake an</hi> Aetna <hi>of deſire was kindled in his breaſt, yet the tender regard he had to her Honour, and the conſideration that one more deſerving than himſelf was already poſſeſt of her Favour, mov'd him to ſuppreſs thoſe flames by abſenting himſelf, which if he had ſtaid would difficultly have been ſtifled; and the rather, becauſe of the anguiſh which to ſee her in anothers em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracements would plunge him into, if he did not ſpeedily withdraw himſelf into ſome remote part, until either the death of his rival ſhould put a period to his jealouſie, or his own ſhould
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170098:18"/>lay thoſe thoughts aſleep which ſuffer'd him li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to take ſo little reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not with more attention than pleaſure, did <hi>Stella</hi> hearken to the words of <hi>Carlo,</hi> who delivered himſelf with ſuch a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and comely Grace, in ſuch appoſite Expreſſions, and ſo movingly ſetting forth the lively ſenſe of his Condition, that ſhe was no longer able to withſtand the force of Love, which, by his winning Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Behaviour, had captivated her Heart: ſhe plainly perceiv'd her ſelf to be the Object of his Love; and aſſur'd her ſelf, that his Love was firm and real ſince for her ſake, and that he might not ſee her in the power of <hi>Alfredo,</hi> he was ſo willing to forſake both Country, Friends, and Kindred, and all thoſe Comforts which thoſe Men muſt needs be depriv'd of, who are ſecluded from their Native Soyl. She hath now plainly found, That her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are wholly ſubdu'd by the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry of <hi>Carlo;</hi> inſomuch, that through the relenting of her Heart toward him ſhe was hardly able to contain her ſelf from requeſting him to deſiſt from his intended Journey; but ſhe was quickly withheld, by the Conſcience which ſhe always made of keeping her Modeſty inviolable, and a certain timorous caution, not to precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170098:19"/>her ſelf raſhly into the choice of a new Lover, having had her Expectation ſo much deceiv'd in the old one. <hi>Alfredo;</hi> who being, for the ſpace of a Night, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented unto her fancy a moſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd and prudent Perſonage, prov'd af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to be nothing leſs than the Man ſhe took him for. Thus taking his fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel of <hi>Stella,</hi> he left her not without ſome ſadneſs and regret for his departure; for ſo it often falls out, that thoſe things which being preſent are lightly eſteem'd, uſe when they are wanted, to leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them a deep ſenſe of their abſence: he put off his journey no longer than till the next day; and becauſe to have been ſilent, at his departure, of thoſe things he had to ſay unto his Brother concerning his unkindneſs toward him, had been to go his journey with a diſquieted and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged mind, he had a deſire to declare himſelf at large unto him. It is not the leaſt of ſatisfactions to a mind agriev'd, and not having any other means to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd, to complain freely of the wrongs receiv'd, unto the party by whom they are offer'd; He hearing that he was at the houſe where <hi>Stella</hi> liv'd, went thither to him, and tali'd him aſide, that he might privately confer with him: <hi>Alfredo</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170098:19"/>to ſend him away with an exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated mind, refus'd not to go aſide with him to know his pleaſure; and the rather, becauſe haply it might be the laſt time he ſhould have to do with him. No ſooner were the two Brothers retir'd unto a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Court that was on the back-ſide of the houſe, but <hi>Stella</hi> having had ſome intimation of the buſineſs, ſhe led by a womans curioſity (a quality incident to that Sex) aſcended up into a Balcone which jutted forth on the ſame ſide; where ſhe ſtood not only ſafe and unſuſpected, but ſo commodiouſly withal, that through a low Lattice, ſhe could both plainly diſcern them, and hear moſt of what they ſaid: Among other things that paſt between them, ſhe might hear <hi>Carlo</hi> in an angry mood ſpeak thus unto his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>Tell me</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Brother, Have I not all the reaſon in the world to tax you of cruelty and infidelity? ſince I having ſo faithfully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to you the good will I bare to</hi> Stella, <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring your aſsiſtance, and you ſeeming to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour my intent; you went about, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this, to bereave me of my content, my hopes, and even my life it ſelf (for, to bereave me of</hi> Stella, <hi>was to bereave me of all theſe) Is it poſsible that there could harbour in your heart ſo high a degree of inhamanity toward me? Had
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170098:20"/>I been a meer ſtranger to you, as I am your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what could you have done more? Nay, had I been your utter Enemy, what greater cruelty could you have offer'd me? If indeed it had appeared to me before I had communicated my mind, that you had been before hand with me in your Addreſſes to her, I ſhould not have thought it ſtrange to ſee my ſelf prevented by you, but ſhould have thought your love groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon vertuous Principles; but that you ſhould promote your ſervice to her, not ſo much out of any real love derived from your own free choice, but meerly that you might diſappoint me of the innocent happineſs I aim'd at, was ſuch a carriage in you, as I both admire and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt: It is a thing ſcarce ever heard of in any ſtory, That one extracted from ſo noble a Race ſhould ſtain his generous blood with a deed ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous. 'Tis true, when I conſider your power and authority, I do not much wonder that your tyranny over me hath been ſo great; for it is not unknown to me how much you have ever ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me: but as oft as I conſider how dear a thing Honour and Reputation is to thoſe that do but pretend to the leaſt Gentility, I am aſtoniſht to think that you ſhould not be aſhem'd, not only to commit ſo much baſeneſs, but even to have the leaſt imagination of it. To be brief.</hi> Alfre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, <hi>I love</hi> Stella, <hi>as you well know; I would to Heaven you had never known it: You are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170098:20"/>now aſpiring to her Nuptials, whileſt I am go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I know not whither, and for no other cauſe, but that I may ſequeſter my ſelf from a place where to live in this unfortunate condition would be worſe than to die a hundred deaths. Know this, That an inſufferable injury may prove of dangerous conſequence, even to the Actor, when it lights upon ſuch a one as knows how to reſent it with diſdain: yet ſince it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that</hi> Stella <hi>meets your Love with equal Ardor, ſo much a Servant I am to her deſires, ſo fearful of being any hinder ance to her content, that, not to diſtaste her in the leaſt meaſure, I am prepar'd to go this Voyage, on purpoſe that I may ſuffer you to enjoy her freely; and may ye enjoy her for multitudes of years, ſo I be not a beholder of your happineſs, which is my unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs: for I verily believe, That if I ſhould ſee her in your embraces, ſuch a torrent of Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie would burſt forth from my enraged breſt, that the whole world would not be able to allay it. Nay, even that night when I thought my ſelf ſo much bleſt by being admitted into her company, ſhe in deteſtation of the love I profeſt to her, ſpake ſo many things ill of me to my ſelf, (thinking without doubt it had been you to whom ſhe ſpake) that had the fervency of my Affection been any whit leſs than it was, I had ſcarce been able to refrain from breaking out into ſome outragious Act; and while you at the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170098:21"/>ſame time came thither to our amazement, and forbid me the place which I had more right to than your ſelf, that I did not then pay you the reward of your treachery, was not for want of courage, or that I was not throughly ſpirited with anger, but becauſe your prudent caution advis'd you to retire your ſelf (and 'tis not ſo ſafe to purſue eagerly a retreating perſon:) and now that I may not be a perpetual moleſtation to you, or zun the hazzard of ruining my ſelf, therefore it is that I betake my ſelf to ſtranger-Countries, haply to meet (if heaven be not the more propitious) with an untimely death; for my life is expos'd to the mercy of a Fortune, which how unſure and deceitful a Guide ſhe hath been to me, the experience of many years hath taught me. Theſe things I ſpeak to you, not that I make account my words will ought more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with you, than if they were ſpoken to the Wind; but that laying them open before you, you may be made conſcious to your ſelf of your unworthy dealings toward me; and that at the remembrance of them, the ſting of your guilty mind may afflict you a little, ſince your cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty hath afflicted me ſo much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alfredo</hi> was both aſham'd and angry at himſelf, that he had endur'd to hear out with patience this ſo peremptory and taunting Speech of his; and attributing that to inordinate Liberty in him, which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170098:21"/>was indeed a juſt reſentment, He told him, <q>That whereas he had tax'd him ſo much of Imperiouſneſſe and Tyranny, he had all the reaſon in the world to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count him merciful, for that he had ſo often ſuffer'd his inſolent carriage to go unpuniſh'd; eſpecially that night when he found him in Diſcourſe with <hi>Stella,</hi> when being attended with his Servants, he had both the power and opportunity to have puniſht him even with death it ſelf.</q> Moreover, he advertiz'd him, <q>That his depriving him of the enjoyment of <hi>Stella,</hi> was not out of envie, but a juſt check to his Arrogance; becauſe that he knowing well how much he hated him, had gone about notwithſtanding to make him a forwarder of his deſires.</q> He added farther, <q>That if he Married her, it was not ſo much for any real love he bare her, as becauſe he diſdain'd that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny attempt which he had undertaken ſhould not ſucceed; for that although ſhe were fair, witty, and nobly deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, yet that in other reſpects ſhe came ſhort of deſerving him.</q> In this ſort had inconſiderate <hi>Alfredo</hi> run on diſparaging <hi>Stella,</hi> had not <hi>Carlo</hi> ſtopt the ſwift car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer of his tongue, by ſaying, <q>That he did unworthily, in ſpeaking any thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170098:22"/>the diſpraiſe of her, and wiſh'd him to be aſſur'd, That if he did not think <hi>Stella</hi> not only to be his equal in deſert, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to be a companion for one far more deſerving than himſelf; his preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on deceiv'd him very much.</q> Adding withal, <q>That he ſhould ſooner be mov'd to draw his Sword in the defence of her fame and vertue, than in his own behalf.</q> He had no ſooner ſpoken theſe words, but <hi>Alfredo</hi> weary of what had been ſaid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and impatient of hearing any more, flung from him in a fume, without giving him any other Anſwer. Upon this, <hi>Carlo</hi> immediately departed thence, and betook himſelf to his own Lodging, to prepare all things in a readineſſe for the taking of his Journey the next day.</p>
            <p>It is not to be expreſt, in what vexation of Spirit, in what ſadneſſe and ſuſpenſion of mind <hi>Stella</hi> remain'd, after ſhe perceiv'd her ſelf ſo palpably undeceiv'd: not able to ſuppreſſe the grief, wherewith her heart went great, ſhe confin'd her ſelf to her Chamber; that ſo breathing out her Complaints to her ſelf, ſhe might have a little eaſe and reſpite from thoſe reſtleſſe paſſions where with her minde was agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: ſhe revolved in her minde the perſon of <hi>Carlo,</hi> his gallant deportment, his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170098:22"/>and above all, his real and noble Intentions: and at length call'd to minde that <hi>Carlo</hi> muſt needs be the man who firſt gave her a teſtimony of his love; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining on the injuſtice of Fortune, that rob'd her eyes of the ſight of him whom ſhe lov'd, and impos'd upon her the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ſo loath'd an object. It was not long ſince <hi>Carlo,</hi> ſmall in her eſteem, did all that might make him worthy of her Service; <hi>Alfredo</hi> inveſted in her favour, did nothing that was not unworthy of it: now <hi>Carlo,</hi> inthron'd in her heart and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, muſt be baniſh'd from her ſight; and <hi>Alfredo,</hi> long ſince caſhiered from her favour, muſt remain to afflict with his Sollicitings: and her minde giving her that the laſt time <hi>Carlo</hi> had been at her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, her eyes had taken their laſt farewel of him; the thought of it drew tears from her eyes, and pierc'd her heart with grief: She was infinitely ſorry in her mind, that his Country and ſhe were to be depriv'd ſo ſoon of him; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading her ſelf that if ſhe were but once more to have come to the Speech of him, her words would have ſo far prevail'd with him as to have retarded his journey, if not to have put an end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; With tears in her eyes, and love in her heart,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170098:23"/>
               <q>Oh <hi>Carlo</hi> (ſaid ſhe) if theſe Complaints of mine, which I breath from the bottom of my heart had wings to flye unto you, they would doubtleſſe be ſo powerful with you, as haply to make you change your reſolution of leaving <hi>Sevil,</hi> at leaſt to depart with the greater contentment of mind; for now ſo ſtrong an Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant have your perfections upon me, that it is in vain for me to flatter my ſelf any longer in thinking that I am able not to love you; the truth and reality of this love, I have but now began ſenſibly to feel, although many days are paſt ſince it firſt took root within me: that to me ſo fortunate night wherein I had the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to diſcourſe with you, there was not any thing you did which I did not admire, nor ſpake you ought which was not wonderfully pleaſing; and from that time forth I was really yours, although I ſeem'd <hi>Alfredo</hi>'s; for it was your va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, your prudence, and diſcreer carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, which enamour'd me of him, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had proceeded from him. It is true, when firſt I knew my ſelf to be lov'd by you, I thought I had ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be offended, thinking it had been your envie toward your Brother that mov'd you to affront me for his ſake;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170098:23"/>but ſince it hath been ſo cleer unto me, that the paſſion you have for my love, hath been ſo conſtant and faithful as not at all to grow cold through ill ſucceſſe, and that on the contrary it was rather out of envie to you, than any true affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to me, that your Brother profeſs'd himſelf my Servant; be aſſur'd, Oh <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> that I am not only not offended with your love, but even ſo pleas'd that I am thought worthy of it, that nothing but death it ſelf, and ſcarce that neither, ſhall have power to make me prove unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. In this one thing I account my ſelf happy, that I may as juſtly, without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being deceiv'd, boaſt my ſelf to have dominion over your heart, as ſhe that hath been both an eye and an eare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſe of the ſame. But whereas I ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you ſo much reſpect, can notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding conſent to ſuffer your abſence, and not yield you the place your vertue deſerves, I ſeem to my ſelf to ſurpaſſe the cruelty of my own Sex: and yet, fool that I am, how do I know, what thoughts you may be apt to conceive of me, if I ſhould go about to ſhew my ſelf but indifferently familiar? for a perſon of quality is above others lyable to bring her fame in queſtion, by ſtriving to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170098:24"/>appear not ungrateful.</q> Thus ſtood ſhe diſcourſing with <hi>Carlo</hi> abſent, as if he had been preſent; and carefully conſidering with her ſelf, that the next morning being determin'd the ultimate time of his ſtay, ſhe could not be permitted the happineſſe of ſeeing him, to perform the dear Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of a parting Lover, ſhe reaſſum'd her old Complaints afreſh; yet having put on a firm reſolution that <hi>Alfredo,</hi> whoſe Service was utterly hateful to her, were he never ſo imperious, never ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate, never ſo much back'd with her Fathers authority, ſhould notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding be conſtrain'd, through her utmoſt neglect of him, to forgo all his intereſt in her; ſhe immediately took in hand (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not without ſome fear of her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) to deal ſo effectually with <hi>Carlo,</hi> as to poſſeſſe him, that his long abſence from <hi>Serail,</hi> would be a means to bring her life in danger: To this end, ſhe forthwith diſpatch'd ſhort Note, deſiring him, <q>He would be pleas'd, the night following, to give her the meeting at the back-gate of her fathers houſe, for that ſhe had to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate unto him a buſineſs that would much import him to know, before his lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Sevil;</hi> and in requital of ſo great an honor, he ſhould receive ſuch ſatisfaction
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170098:24"/>touching the Effect of his conſtant love to her, as perhaps would be unto him no leſſe welcom than unexpected.</q> No ſooner was the morning come, but ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd this Letter to her Maid (the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of all her Secrets) bidding her <q>To enquire for <hi>Carlo</hi>'s Lodgings, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him with the Letter ſo privately, that no body ſhould be preſent at the delivery of it.</q> All that her Miſtris commanded, the Maid punctually perform'd in every circumſtance; and came at the very ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that <hi>Carlo</hi> was wholly taken up with his Friends and Kindred; when calling him aſide, ſhe delivered her Meſſage and Letter; telling him withal, <q>That ſhe was not to ſtay his Anſwer, partly leſt it might be diſcern'd who ſhe was, by ſome curious pryer into Secrets; and partly becauſe the Letter requir'd not to be Anſwer'd at preſent, but in the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and that by himſelf in perſon.</q> He ſtood for a while aſtoniſh'd at this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dream'd of news. but knowing there was that with him which could eaſily diſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him (for he knew it to be <hi>Stella</hi>'s hand) he broke up the Seals; and after having ſlightly glanc'd over the contents, and ruminated many things to himſelf he began to enter into a ſerious debate, what
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170098:25"/>might be the reaſon that mov'd her to ſend him this requeſt, whenas he was fully poſſeſt, not only that he was not favor'd of her himſelf, but that ſhe having given her hear already to <hi>Alfredo,</hi> was ſhortly to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her hand in Marriage: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he was altogether impatient t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll he had obey'd her deſire; he would fam have put off his Journey for a while longer; which could difficultly be done, both in regard that between him and the Friends who were met together, the fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel-Salutations had already paſt; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe almoſt all the people of the City were flock'd together in heaps to ſee him paſſe out of Town: ſo that he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd at leaſt to counterfeit a departure. He went forth accompanied with the chief Gentlemen of the City, and was bid adieu by the loud exclamations of the multitude; carrying along with him out of Town as much happineſſe and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from the voyces of the people, as he left troubles and vexations behind him in his Brothers tyranny. It was not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Fame convey'd this unwelcom news unto the ears of diſconſolate <hi>Stella:</hi> to think that he ſhould ſet ſolittle by her kind proffer, afflicted her mind with the bittereſt ſorrow that could be imagin'd,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170098:25"/>and made her repent that ſhe had any way manifeſted her love to him; reſolving thenceforward to hold this for a maxime, <q>That for a Lady to confer her favours on any man, is the only way to make him prove perfidious and ingrateful.</q> She accus'd her ſelf as inconſiderate, for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring over-haſtily to impart her courteſies, ſince ſo unfortunately they had lighted upon one that either diſtruſted, or diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded them. By this time the day-light, as it were diſmay'd at the blackneſſe and deformity of night, had hid it ſelf under the ſhadow of the earth; when <hi>Stelia</hi> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing upon ſome or other occaſion to go into that place, where the night before ſhe had been a witneſſe of <hi>Carlo</hi>'s Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſhe might diſcern a man, who ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well acquainted with every part of the Court, fixed him ſelf in the middle of it; and looking more intently upon him, ſhe ſtrongly conjectur'd that either her eyes deceiv'd her, or by the Majeſty of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſhould be <hi>Carlo:</hi> Nor was ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed miſtaken; for he having, with ſome difficulty, diſ-engag'd himſelf from the Company that attended him, made a ſhift to return back, to ſee his beloved <hi>Stella,</hi> and to know what ſhe had to command: And hearing ſome little noiſe about the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170098:26"/>window, he call'd by her name the Maid that had brought him the Letter in the morning; upon which <hi>Stella</hi> knew him by his voice: and that ſhe might not loſe the opportunity which the time and place of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd her, ſhe immediately diſcover'd her ſelf; and after ſhe had related to him the falſe Title that his proud Brother preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to her, the miſtake that hapned many nights ago, the much wherewith his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and diſcretion had enamour'd her, the means ſhe took to diſdeceive her ſelf, the reaſon that mov'd her to love him, and how bitterly ſhe reſented his abſence; ſhe continued thus:</p>
            <p>
               <q>It was for no other reaſon, <hi>Carlo,</hi> that I writ to you, than to endeavour to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert your intended voyage: and you may well think, that before I could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with my ſelf to put ſuch a deſign in practice, it coſt me many a ſorrowful tear: and it is a uſual art (among women highly born) to keep their flames ſo, not to be diſcover'd by any, unleſſe by their ſecret tears and ſighs, that in time they grow too maſterleſſe for either their breaſts to be able to contain, or their eyes to diſſemble them. Heaven knows what frequent and painful conflicts I have had with my Honor, till in the end,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170098:26"/>my Affections prevail'd more with me than my Fame; ſo that I am confirm'd in this truth, That to be able to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ones ſelf (eſpecially in things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the vehement deſires of the Soul) is a work rather of Practice than of Contemplation. You ſee, <hi>Carlo,</hi> how much the night befriends me in hiding my bluſhes; which makes me the rather preſume to be ſo plain and free with you as I am, not putting any falſe gloſſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my words. In fine, I am devoted yours; and of all men living, you are he alone that ſhall have power to diſpoſe of my heart: The wealth that my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath abundantly to ſpare, is of it ſelf ſo ſofficient, that you may have where with to live ſplendidly, and yet not need to be beholding to your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the leaſt ſupply. All the favors he can boaſt to have received from me, are ſo few, ſo ſlight, that to have ſhow'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Gentleman for one nights space, would have much more conduc'd to the advancement of his hopes. Impute not (I requeſt you) this my freedom to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impudence in me, but rather to thoſe your irreſiſtable Charms that have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flav'd my Affection to you; nor think me guilty of any great Grime in laboring
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170098:27"/>to requite him with love, of whom I have been ſo much belov'd; who hath been ſo eminent in conſtancy, as to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reſpect me, although rejected by me. I appeal to your ſelf, whether you think it is ordinary with men, to love with ſo much truth and faithfulneſſe? I profeſs to ye, That were you not endued with thoſe perfections that cauſe me to little leſs than idolize you, your loyalty &amp; firmneſs would be ſufficient of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to endear you to me. And be aſſur'd, howſoever Fortune deals with me, whether your firſt Reſolution be more powerful with you to hold on your jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or my late invitation to you to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your mind, I am prepar'd to receive either condition with as equal a minde as it is poſſible for me; at leaſt, I ſhall have attain'd to this degree of contentment, That I have given a little earneſt of the much that I am indebted to you.</q> With attentive admiration <hi>Carlo</hi> heard her ſpeak theſe things, whereby it grew apparent to him, by what means it came to paſſe, that <hi>Stella</hi> was ſo melted in her rigour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him: with a graceful humility he render'd her thanks for the great and new favour ſhe had done him, as far from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected as deſerv'd; promiſing that to ſerve
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170098:27"/>her he was ready to become her very ſlave. The concluſion of this amorous Diſcourſe, was, that ſhe gave him her hand, in token that ſhe unfeignedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd to be his Wife. By this, the royal Sun had ſummon'd the day to appear, while he with his beams gilded the tops of the weſtern Groves, when <hi>Carlo</hi> took his leave of her, with a purpoſe to divide his time between two eſteemed perſons; in the day-time, to huſh himſelf up in the houſe of <hi>Leonardo,</hi> a Gentleman of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, his intimate friend; in the night, to viſit his Miſtreſs <hi>Stella?</hi> which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving vow'd to perform as oft as the night came, he went to find out <hi>Leonardo,</hi> to whom he communicated the particulars of his whole ſucceſſe. There paſt many nights and days, wherein there interceded between theſe two Lovers ſuch familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as was not inconſiſtent with modeſty and civility. <hi>Stella,</hi> all this while, had much ado to forbear betraying by her looks the diſturbance which was in her minde, ſeeing <hi>Alfredo</hi> ſtill continu'd to haunt her with his fooliſh importunities; and her Father having found her at firſt plyable to his deſires, ſhe had promis'd him, that which both her honour and her ſecond choice injoyn'd her not to conſent
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170098:28"/>to. The very next time <hi>Carlo</hi> and ſhe met, ſhe declar'd unto him her Fathers cares and watchfulneſs over her ways, and unto what difficult ſtreights their counſels were like to be reduc'd. Theſe words ſorely perplexed the poor Gentleman; who ntiſtruſting that through <hi>Stella</hi>'s fear, and obſervance of her Fathers pleaſure, his hopes might be in danger to miſcarry, told her, <q>That if ſhe found her love was not powerful enough to reſiſt thoſe ſtronger Obligations before mention'd, ſhe had beſt to conſult with her own minde, and do as ſhe thought fit; that for his part, he had been ſo accuſtom'd to the brunt of adverſe Fortune, as that he ſhould not count it any new miſhap, although the greateſt that had yet befaln him.</q> He would have ſaid ſomthing more, but that through the ſuddenneſſe and greatneſſe of his paſſion, he became as mute and motionleſſe as a marble Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Whereupon ſhe, to take from him all that might give him cauſe to ſuſpect her reality, affirm'd, that when ſhe firſt made her love known unto him, it was not out of any other deſign, than an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned intention that he only ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy her; and therefore ſhe purpoſed (the better to free her ſelf from the perſecution
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170098:28"/>of her Fathers carefulneſſe, and <hi>Alfredo</hi>'s troubleſomneſſe) to let him in at a private gate, the night following, which ſhould ſtand ready open for him; that ſo her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (when he ſhould come and ſee him with her, and finde him to be of the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame extraction with <hi>Alfredo,</hi> ſeeing no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means left to preſerve his daughters honour) might give way to the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of their lawful and honeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carlo</hi> overjoy'd to hear a matter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd ſo likely to take effect, was ſcarce able to expreſſe how much he reſented her continu'd favours; and wiſh'd that ſhe could have read his heart in his eyes, that her courteſies might the ſooner appear to have been beſtow'd upon a perſon that knew not to be ingrateful; and that if he had been born to the whole Empire of the World, as he was deſtin'd but to low Fortunes, (though he were a Gentleman) he would have been nevertheleſſe ready to have proſtrated himſelf at her feet; proteſting, that his Fates could not have confer'd a more contented eſtate upon him, than to have render'd him worthy to enjoy her beauty. By this the morning having diſplay'd her Lilies in the Eaſt, <hi>Carlo</hi> was fain to retire himſelf from his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170098:29"/>beloved ſtation. Never had any day been ſo tedious to him, as was this, wherein he thought Time perform'd his courſe more lazily than he was wont: but the day, and his reſtleſſe expectation, had at length an end. No ſooner was the wiſhed night re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, but he haſted out of doors, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with his friend <hi>Leonardo;</hi> whom leaving at the entrance of the Court, to guard (if need were) that part of the houſe, he went directly toward the window: he had but touch'd it with his Sword, when he might diſcern a glimpſe of his beautiful Sun, whom love had made diligent to obſerve her time ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly. After ſhe had fetch'd a turn about the houſe to make ſure all things, leaving her Father in bed, and the reſt of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily retir'd every one to their reſts, unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied of any but her Servant-Maid (a fit coadjutor for ſuch an enterprize) ſhe came back to <hi>Carlo;</hi> and firſt giving him a brief admoniſhment how much it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hov'd him to continue reſolv'd and firm to his firſt engagement, that if ever he ſhould happen to prove ſo much a meer man, as to grow cold in his Affection, he ſhould yet be careful not to let ſlip out of his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, how much ſhe had ſuffer'd for his ſake, how many dangers undergone; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170098:29"/>ſhe directed him to go about to the falſe gate of her houſe, where ſhe would be ready to receive him. While he obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to her will, was about to perform her directions; and ſhe gone to expect him at the place appointed, there hapned to meet him in the ſtreet, through which he was to paſs, a great company of people, whom by their multitude he gheſs'd to be the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-watch: he thought it not expedient that they ſhould ſee him enter <hi>Stella</hi>'s houſe: and to have ſtaid their coming up to him, would have made him in danger of being diſcover'd by them; therefore he reſolv'd to avoid the ſtreet till they were paſt by: and ſo ſtealing by them, he and his Friend ſlipt into the next houſe they ſaw open. The ſtreet was wholly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with the great number of thoſe that came in queſt of theſe two; who ſeeing them nowhere to be found, and diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that two men ſhould be able to baffle the hopes of ſo many, they divided them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into ſeveral companies, the better to be able to ſearch every corner of the ſtreet. And <hi>Carlo,</hi> as ſoon as they were diſperſt, thinking the coaſt had been cleer, he told his friend <hi>Leonardo,</hi> that now, if he pleas'd, he might return to his own houſe, for any thing that was now to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170098:30"/>be done, which would either require his company or his aſſiſtance: and ſo ventur'd abroad again, as being fully perſwaded, that the people he had ſeen, were no other than the Watch, that nightly were to walk about, to ſee if any tumult or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order were ſtirring in the City: but he was deceiv'd; for his Brother <hi>Alfredo,</hi> out of a capricious perſeverance in his Suit to <hi>Stella,</hi> becauſe he would needs ſhew himſelf to have omitted no pains, no ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe, nor vigilancy to win her impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable heart, went accompanied with all his train of Servants to viſit her; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by chance eſpy'd, about the entrance into the Court, two men who ſeem'd to ſlink away fearful of being diſcover'd, he commanded ſome of his followers to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue them, and not to return till they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd who they were; and deſtitute of company as he was, went directly toward <hi>Stella</hi>'s houſe; juſt at that juncture of time, when ſhe, according to her appointment, was come to open the door, and her arms, to her expected Lover; telling him, (for ſhe thought it had been <hi>Carlo</hi>) in the moſt endearing terms that could be imagin'd, <hi>That he was happily come to receive the reward of his fidelity. Alfredo</hi> knew well, that he was not the man, to whom theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170098:30"/>were intended; but imagin'd that one of the Maid-ſervants of the houſe was to ſteal a Meeting with her Sweet-heart at this appointed hour; and that being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by the darkneſſe of the night, and his deſign, ſhe had miſtaken him for her Enamorado: therefore he reſolv'd to lay hold upon this opportunity for the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acceſſe to the ſight and ſpeech of his Miſtris. And ſo, invited by the falſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of her that op'ned the door, he follow'd her in, wrapping his face up in his Cloak, that he might not be diſcern'd by her; who, not leſſe aſham'd than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, led him up ſtairs into her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, which ſhe thought to be a place where ſhe might entertain him with the greateſt freedom. By this time <hi>Carlo</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving at the houſe, had only not reach'd the door, when it was ſhut againſt him by the Maid; to whom the ſad Lover call'd out, and pray'd her to tell her Lady that <hi>Carlo</hi> was now at the door awaiting her promis'd Favours, and that ſhe ſhould not long be ignorant of the accident that detain'd him from her ſo long. <hi>How can this be,</hi> (reply'd the Maid) <hi>whenas</hi> Carlo <hi>is already enter'd, and poſſeſt of thoſe Favours which you ſpeak of? Carlo</hi> at firſt ſuſpended with admiration, came neer enough to be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170098:31"/>diſcover'd by her; who when ſhe knew him, was ſtrangely ſurpriz'd at this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter; and almoſt dead with amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, confuſedly related to him, that a certain man, who he was ſhe knew not, coming juſt as her Lady was op'ning the door, took advantage of her miſtake, and ſlipt in without being diſcover'd. <hi>Carlo</hi> aſham'd that his reſentment was not powerful enough to take away his life, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly intreated her to open him the door, leſt the growth of this miſtake might proceed to the ruine of his deareſt hopes. She opened him the door; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling him ſo to bridle in his paſſion, as that it might not break forth into any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance, to the betraying or endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering of either of them; and with much intreaty (for he was all on fire to unwind this intricate deceipt) ſhe led him to the Chamber, where finding the door lock'd, he quickly eſpy'd a creviſe, through which it was no hard matter for him to diſcern plainly whatever was done in the Chamber: he perceiv'd <hi>Stella</hi> with a Dagger in her hand, reſolutely defending her ſelf againſt <hi>Alfredo;</hi> to whom, both weeping and inrag'd, ſhe ſpake thus: <hi>So great is the rudeneſs that you have ſhewn in this diſorderly action, ſo great the diſgrace I ſuffer
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170098:31"/>in your raſhneſs, that I ſhould have much ado to forbear bathing my Steel in your infamous blood, before you ſtir out of this place, if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of my honour did not more withhold me, than any humour I have to put up ſo villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous an affront; but I ſwear by heaven, Though I am a woman, and hinder'd by the imbecility of my ſex, from making your life a ſacrifice to my juſt anger and revenge; yet I will at leaſt ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to knew who you are, that ye may not live ſecure from my rage, though you ſhould obſcure your ſelf in the bowels of the earth; for outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of this nature, as they cannot be excus'd from blame, ſo they ought not to remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſh'd: I invited you in, 'tis true; but it was becauſe I thought you to be the man, who is tomorrow morning to be my Spouſe: at length, miſtruſting ſome deceit, I could not but ſeek the ſatisfaction of knowing who you were; but your face was ſo muffled, your whiſpers ſo low, that I could not inform my ſelf either by your countenance or voice who you ſhould be: no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if after my earneſt, but vain endeavours to know you, your obſtinate ſilence render'd you ſuſpected to me. Nor had I leſs reaſon to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, when being both alone, and a woman, I perceiv'd it your deſign, by obſcuring your ſelf, to deprive me of the hopes of diſcovering your impoſture: but whoever you are, I have reaſon to conclude, that you are not the perſon whom I
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170098:32"/>expected; ſeeing your actions are ſo little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to that nobleneſs and civility which alwayes accompanies his behaviour, and that you are no other than of the meaneſt and rudeſt ſort of men: he, whom ſhame forceth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal his face, is made to diſcover the falſity of his heart. I had call'd out to raiſe the Family, if I had not fear'd that my Fathers paſsion, ſhould he find me in ſuch a ſtate as this, would hinder him from giving ear to any reaſon I ſhould alleadge to juſtifie my innocency; ſo that I have put my ſelf upon this defenſive poſture; and Heaven hath been ſo favourable to me, as to permit me the means both of oppoſing your vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanous intentions, and of being able to quit this wretched life, rather than conſent, in the leaſt manner, to my own diſhonour: therefore reſolve ſuddenly what it is you would with me; for if you ſhall dare to attempt any thing ignoble upon my perſon, you ſhall ſoon ſeeme weltring in my bloud, and your deſign made fruſtrate by my death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carlo</hi>'s minde was pretty well pacified, when he ſaw how ill it ſucceeded with the unknown in his baſe enterprize, and with what courage <hi>Stella</hi> defended her ſelf from whatever violence he might of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer: but he became inflam'd with a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous deſire to make it appear to her, how highly he reſented the injury that was
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170098:32"/>offer'd her, and that he wanted neither force nor courage to revenge it. He or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the Maid to run in haſte into her Chamber, and to give out, <hi>That her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter was coming:</hi> whereat <hi>Stella</hi> was as much troubled, as <hi>Alfredo</hi> amaz'd; his haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty heart condeſcended to wiſh that he had been out of the houſe at that inſtant: yet when he bethought himſelf, how much affection and good will the Old man had for him, he boldly op'ned the door, as ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hoping that this might prove advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to his deſign, than fearing it would be any hinderance to it; but he was ſcarce out of the Chamber, when he ſaw his Brother comming toward him, who ſetting his Sword to his breaſt, threatned him with preſent death, unleſſe he would inſtantly declare to him who he was: So ſurprized was <hi>Alfredo</hi> at this Rancontre, that what he heard and ſaw before his eyes, he could ſcarce believe to be any other than a dream; perceiving him preſent, whom he ſuppos'd to have been many miles off. It was not a little confuſion to him, to behold <hi>Carlo</hi> with fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in his looks, ſtill perſiſt in his menacing demand: Nevertheleſſe he made this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Anſwer, <hi>That he would as ſoon conſent to be cut in pieces as to declare his name; but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170098:33"/>That if he eſteem'd his own puiſſance ſuch, as to be able to extort from him a confeſſion of his name, he might (if he pleas'd to repair to the ſtreet which was neer at hand, and a place much fitter to decide ſuch controverſies in) give teſtimony of it, with more honor and ſafety to himſelf, and with leſs hazard to the reputation of</hi> Stella. The thing which he propos'd was not more pleaſing to <hi>Carlo</hi> than di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſteful to <hi>Stella,</hi> who thought her ſelf as much concern'd in his well or ill being, as if one life had been common to them both; and would by all means have hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd their purpoſe, but knew not how. <hi>Carlo</hi> went forth follow'd by <hi>Alfredo,</hi> who beheld him with a world of envie, ſince he had ſo plainly diſcover'd, that he was become abſolute Lord of <hi>Stella</hi>'s af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and that it was he whom ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and in ſtead of whom he himſelf was admitted into her Chamber. Who would have thought, that had but heard <hi>Alfredo</hi> word it ſo reſolutely with <hi>Carlo,</hi> and ſo freely to appoint a meeting, that he had not been of the moſt valiant? but it was indeed upon this confidence only, that his followers, in whoſe obedience he repoſed much truſt, had ſeen him enter into the houſe, and were ſtanding at the door to attend his coming forth: yet ſo
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170098:33"/>cunningly masked his cowardice, that it caus'd <hi>Stella</hi> to have much trouble and fear for the ſafety of her loved <hi>Carlo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At length, into the ſtreet went the two adverſe Brothers, but with far different Reſolutions; for whereas <hi>Carlo</hi> thought of nothing leſſe than being avenged of his Enemy; <hi>Alfredo</hi> was on the other ſide much diſmay'd when he look'd round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, and ſaw not one man in the ſtreet except his adverſary; for it ſeems thoſe that came along with him, weary of tracing to and fro the ſtreet, returned to the place where they had left their Lord; but finding him not there, they were gone to ſeek him in ſome houſes of recreation, which for his divertiſement he was wont to viſit, which ſtood ready open at all hours to entertain thoſe of the moſt principal of that place. <hi>Alfredo</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the valour of his enraged Brother, and ſomwhat diſtruſtful of his own, told him (to hinder if it were poſſible by ſome excuſe the drawing of Swords) <hi>That he had ſo much love and affection for that Lady, as that he would not that any tumult or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief ſhould happen ſo neer the place of her dwelling; therefore he thought it more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient that they ſhould retire into the next ſtreet, where they might more freely determine, by the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170098:34"/>diſpute of their ſwords, whether of them had the greateſt intereſt in her.</hi> The motion <hi>Carlo</hi> willingly accepted, as thinking that none ought to be more tender of <hi>Stella</hi>'s honour than himſelf; who in the mean while ſuſpicious of the event, <hi>Ay me!</hi> (ſaid ſhe, all bathed in her tears, which were able to make the rocks ſenſible) <hi>Who would have thought, that ſo hopeful a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as our loves had, ſhould be attended with ſuch improſperous ſucceſs? What avails it me to have been favourable to</hi> Carlo<hi>'s paſsion, and to be diſdeceiv'd in the Opinion I had of his indeſerts, when this very night, wherein I made full account to have been intirely his, I ſee my ſelf in ſuch danger of utterly loſing him? O Love! how certain is it, that one ſorrow wherewith thou of flicteſt us, countervaileth all thoſe joyes which thy aliurements promiſe to us! I know not what Witchcraft it is wherewith thou inveigleſt mens minds; but ſure it is, thou treateſt all diſcourteouſly, and yet all follow thee; thou deceiveſt all, and yet all admire thee: It muſt needs be, that Heaven hath inveſted thee with ſome ſecret vertue, to make thee ſo charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that thoſe who have cauſe to complain of thee, ſollicite thee; thoſe whom thou rejecteſt, adhere unto thee. O cordial poyſon, which at once both comforteſt and killeſt! Deceitful fire, which burneſt without conſuming! Sweet Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170098:34"/>which Oppreſſeſt all, yet makeſt all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to be Oppreſſed by thee! In fine, Thou art a Univerſal Tragedy, that ſmileſt at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, yet art accompanied with diſuſtrous ends. There is no condition to which thou art not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious. When one loves, the other diſdains, what deſpair enſueth? When both love, yet are debarr'd injoyment, what impatience it breeds? If ſeparated, what dejectedneſs? If affected with Jealouſie, what trouble and diſquietudes? But, if being Married, through intereſt of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, they both happen to diſguſt each other, what greater miſery can be imagin'd?</hi> With theſe, and ſuch like diſcourſes, ſought the diſconſolate <hi>Stella</hi> to divert the violence of her paſſion, when looking into the ſtreet after the two Duelliſts, and ſeeing neither the one nor the other appear, ſhe began firſt to revolve in her minde, what ſhould have betided them; next, to doubt of the event; and laſtly, to have ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous thoughts for the ſafety of her Lover; nor could ſhe refrain from fearing (though ſhe ſtrove to ſuppreſs that imagination) leſt he might be either wounded or ſlain: but to free her ſelf from the perplexity of theſe tormenting doubts, ſhe reſolv'd to attempt a thing, which though it ſeem'd ſomwhat inconſiſtent with the decency of a virgins behaviour, yet might be excus'd
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170098:35"/>by the violence of a Lovers paſſion; well knowing, that whatever ſhe could do for <hi>Carlo,</hi> could not be lyable to a deeper cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure than what ſhe had already done, in profeſſing ſhe had deſign'd him to be her Husband. So that ſhe went boldly into the ſtreets, leaving her Maid to ſtand cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinel at the door; and paſſing the firſt, ſhe came to the place where <hi>Carlo</hi> behaving himſelf with much gallantry preſs'd hard upon the life of his Antagoniſt, who leſſe couragious than his late bravado pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd, in ſtead of manfully defending him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, began to complain of his Brothers preſumption, and to queſtion him how he, knowing him to be <hi>Alfredo,</hi> durſt offer ſo great a violence to his perſon? But <hi>Carlo</hi> tranſported with anger at the memory of former injuries, and reſolv'd not to ſuffer any longer under his Imperious Envie, vow'd not to treat him as a Brother, but as an Enemy. By this, <hi>Stella</hi> approach'd ſo neer, that him whom wilful ſilence and his muffled countenance withheld from her knowledge in the chamber, ſhe could now eaſily diſcern to be <hi>Alfredo;</hi> and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into what danger the valour of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo</hi> had reduc'd his life, foreſeeing the evil which would accompany his death, for that it would be the means of her Lovers
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170098:35"/>baniſhment, and ſo deprive her at once both of his preſence and her own life, ſhe interpos'd her ſelf between the two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batants, juſt at the juncture of time, when <hi>Alfredo,</hi> through haſte to avoid his enemies fury, having ſtumbled and fallen to the ground, <hi>Carlo</hi> was about to give that fatal blow which was to have put a period to his wretched days, if at the ſame inſtant he had not beheld ſomthing like an Angel ſtand ready to defend that life which he ſought to take away; at which he held his hand, and ſaw that to be <hi>Stella,</hi> which he had but even now taken for ſome heavenly Apparition; who giving way that <hi>Alfre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> might riſe, ſpake to him in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;</p>
            <p>
               <q>Is it poſſible, <hi>Alfredo,</hi> that being born great, and having had the faireſt oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities that might be, to know the world, you ſhould not yet know that Love is a thing not to be gain'd by any force or compulſion; and that the Will hath ſo abſolute a freedom in it ſelf, as not to be over-rul'd by any power leſſe than Heaven it ſelf? You think, belike, that to ſubdue a Lady's Affection is the ſame thing with batt'ring down a Wall, or taking in a ſtrong Fortreſſe; but you deceive your ſelf: for the Ice is not more
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170098:36"/>obdurate againſt the piercing guſts of the North-wind, than a Womans heart againſt the importunity of an indiſcreet Lover. Perhaps you will tell me, that you did it thinking to weary me out with your inceſſant Sollicitations, eſpecially ſince your flames had not arriv'd unto this hight of Ardour, had they not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd nouriſhment from the reſpect wherewith I ſeem'd to treat you at the beginning of your Addreſſe. To this I ſhall Anſwer at a more convenient ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. That which I ſhall now ſay, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, That in deſpite of all your tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous practices to hinder our Loves, it may plainly appear to you, if you are not blind, by the ſame token to which but even now you have been witneſſe, that the love and reſpect I have for <hi>Carlo,</hi> is no leſſe than what is due to a Husband: And know this, That when a Woman of my condition is driven ſo openly and freely to declare her paſſion, to go about to remove it, is no other thing than to attempt impoſſibilities. But becauſe of the unſeaſonableneſſe of the time, and for fear of what inconveniences would follow, if our late ſtirring ſhould have caus'd any diſquietude to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I muſt not conſent to any longer
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170098:36"/>delay's in this place; you therefore I commend to your Lodging and repoſe: as for your Brother, he may (if he pleaſe) henceforth account my habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stella</hi> had not quite made an end of her laſt words, before <hi>Alfredo,</hi> pierc'd to the heart with envie and deſpair, went away, caſting about in his minde all ways where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he might be reveng'd. <hi>Carlo</hi> on the contrary remain'd ſo joyful &amp; contented, as if it had ſeem'd to him, that Fortune weary of perſecuting him, had reſerv'd no more afflictions for him: but he that was born to be the object of her malice, ſoon found his imaginations to be but <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera's;</hi> for Heaven had decreed to imbit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the glory of this his Conqueſt with ſuch variety of misfortunes, that he might in ſome ſort have been ſaid to be a gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, if he had not gain'd the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his hopes. It hapned, while <hi>Stella</hi> was deciding the quarrel between the two Brothers, that her Father having been wakened by the noiſe which their ſtirring in the houſe had made not long before, and not being able again to compoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſleep, for thinking what might be the cauſe of it, he choſe rather to riſe and ſatisfie himſelf of his doubt, than to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170098:37"/>watch the whole night out in ſuch a tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſuſpenſion of minde: and ſo taking his Hat and Cloak, and calling one of his Servants to light him, he went to all the avenues, and ſearch'd every corner of the houſe; being reſolv'd either to pacifie or confirm his jealouſies: nor did he leave any probable cauſe unſuſpected, except his daughters entertaining <hi>Carlo;</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of her words, the modeſt compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of her countenance, the reſervedneſs and decorum which ſhe duely obſerv'd in all her actions, render'd her reputation ſo unſpotted, that it would have been the moſt hard thing in the world to have poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt him with the leaſt prejudice againſt her integrity. That which he had moſt to ſuſpect, was, leſt ſome one, who thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted after his wealth, had watch'd an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to eaſe him of as much of it as they could; willing rather to purchaſe it at ſo eaſie a rate, than to take a journey for it to the Indies as he had done. At length he came to the place where the centinel-Maid ſtood, expecting the return of the two Lovers; who well aware of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters coming, before he could approach neer enough to ſee her, had betaken her ſelf to a ſecret place to hide her from his ſight: but ſo diſtracted ſhe was with this
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170098:37"/>ſudden ſurprizal, that ſhe forgot to take the Key out of the door. the Old man wonder'd at it, but imputed it to the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe of the Servant that had been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd that night to ſhut the doors; and ſo leaving them faſt lock'd himſelf, he took out the Key, and returned back to his Chamber, to compoſe himſelf again to his reſt. In the mean while <hi>Carlo</hi> and <hi>Stella</hi> were come back ſecure of any ſuch great misfortune: <hi>Carlo</hi> call'd to the Maid to open them the door; but ſeeing himſelf (after many call's unanſwer'd) he concluded that ſhe was fallen aſleep; but ſhe, as ſoon as ſhe was aſſur'd of her Maſters being retir'd, was about to have return'd again to the diſcharge of her Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which his coming had interrupted, and to ſee if ſhe could diſcover the return of the two Lovers: But when ſhe came and found the Key miſſing, ſhe preſently call'd to minde the error ſhe had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in leaving it in the door when ſhe went to hide her ſelf; and going into the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cone, ſhe found them arriv'd, and related to them all that had hapned. <hi>Stella,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were that ſhe ſaw <hi>Carlo</hi> too much troubled already to be farther afflicted with her lamentations, or that the exceſs of her grief obſtructed the paſſage of her
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170098:38"/>words, uttered nothing but ſighs which ſhe fetch'd from the very bottom of her heart; and lifted up her eyes to heaven, to which ſhe ſeem'd to complain of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny injuries wherewith Fortune had trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her. <hi>Carlo</hi> beheld her with pity, and wiſh'd her to conſider that all theſe croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes came upon her meerly for his ſake; and that it was only becauſe ſhe lov'd him, that ſhe was ſo toſs'd upon the waves of adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; and that he was ſo much more affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for her misfortunes than his own, that he could willingly have conſented to ſacrifice his life to her quiet, and to the freeing her from thoſe croſſe influences which ſhe participated of with him. <q>Ye do well, <hi>Carlo,</hi> (anſwer'd <hi>Stella</hi>) knowing that I am ſo much yours, as that I ſleight all dangers to make ſure of your ſafety, to be ſo ready to forſake your life to pleaſe me; preſenting me with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of diſcomforts, at a time when I ſtand moſt in need of encouragement. But what is it (I beſeech you) that cauſeth in you this willingneſſe to die (if, as you ſay, no afflictions are grievous to you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than I am concern'd in them) whenas you ought to be confident that your life is the ſole cauſe that makes me have a deſire to live? Ah, my <hi>Carlo,</hi> what
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170098:38"/>greater content can there accrue to me, than to ſee you live long and happie? Conſider that I am devoted to you, and that if I have expreſs'd a deep ſence of this misfortune, it is for your ſake that I reſent it more, than for what I my ſelf ſuffer; ſo long as I am with you, there can nothing ſo ſad or diſaſtrous befal me, that ſhall have power to move me to any great dejection of minde. Diſpoſe of me according to your pleaſure, and bring me to what place you ſhall think moſt convenient, where I may live conceal'd from my Fathers ſight until his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be over paſs'd; and he at length fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding me diſpos'd of ſo much to my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, may applaud both his own Fortune and mine, for having given him a Son-in-law ſo noble, me a Husband ſo ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous.</q> 
               <hi>Carlo</hi> expreſſing himſelf infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joyful, gave her thanks for the high fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours wherewith ſhe had oblig'd him, as briefly as the time and place requir'd: and muſing a while with himſelf what courſe they were beſt to take, it was not long ere he reſolv'd upon the houſe of his friend <hi>Leonardo</hi> for a ſafe retreat to him and his Lady, where they might conſult at leaſure for their own advantage. The maid was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to remain in her Maſters houſe, to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170098:39"/>run the hazard of thoſe inconveniences that attended her, in caſe it ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered that ſhe was a party in her yong Ladies fault; and therefore being let down from the Balcone, by the help of <hi>Carlo,</hi> ſhe went along with him and <hi>Stella:</hi> being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd at <hi>Leonardo</hi>'s houſe, they related to him all that had hapned; and repoſing much confidence in the counſel of ſo faithful a friend, they beſought him to give them his beſt aſſiſtance and advice in this extremity whereinto they were plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; which he faithfully did; telling them, <q>That being it could be no way ſafe for them to remain there, he thought it would be moſt expedient for them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the morning light, to retire to a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Country-houſe of his, about three Leagues from the City, beautified with Fountains and delightful Gardens.</q> And to that end, he immediately gave order to one of his Servants to make ready his own Coach; and commanded him to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and to obſerve them with the ſame reſpect as if it were to his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Carlo</hi> and <hi>Stella</hi> having rendred him thanks in ſuch affectionate expreſſions as ſhew'd how highly they reſented this ſo great Favour, took their leaves, and pray'd him, <q>That he would be careful to give
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170098:39"/>them notice from time to time what ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors or effects this flight of theirs would produce in the City, and what apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions the Old man would have of it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The minde of <hi>Stella,</hi> conſidering the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Scenes of Chance ſhe had run through in the ſpace of two days, was by this time fluctuating in the midſt of many various and doubtful thoughts; but when ſhe bethought herſelf, that all theſe diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances were but to make way for her to the free enjoyment of her lov'd <hi>Carlo,</hi> ſhe reſolv'd to bear them with an undaunted patience. <hi>Carlo</hi> pretended to all that were in the Village, that <hi>Stella</hi> was his Siſter, leſt the Country-people reſorting to the City, might haply in their common diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes let fall ſome paſſage or other ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their diſcovery. Thus concealing both their Conditions and their Name, they liv'd for a while contented and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure. But <hi>Carlo</hi>'s malevolent Planet not yet weary of afflicting him, found out new and unexpected means to complete the number of his ſorrows; and to effect this work, there was an Agent provided, the fitteſt that could have been imagin'd; it was the daughter of him who had the overſeeing of <hi>Leonardo</hi>'s Gardens; ſhe was a Virgin, of perſon not unhandſom, brisk
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170098:40"/>and lively in her behaviour; and of a wit more penetrating, than from one of her birth could have been expected; who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Carlo</hi> ſo many graces &amp; attracts wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy both to be admir'd &amp; lov'd, entertain'd a paſſion for him, ſo unbridled, that it could ſcarce avoid the ſuſpition of <hi>Stella</hi> her ſelf. But as for <hi>Carlo,</hi> his imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was ſo intirely imploy'd in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating the perfections of his Miſtris, that there was no ſpace left void for any other thoughts to enter. <hi>Leonardo</hi> was us'd to viſit them every night, to ſee how they far'd in their new habitation; and to give them notice how their affairs ſucceeded: but one time above the reſt, he enjoyn'd <hi>Carlo,</hi> as he tender'd his ſafety, not to ſtir abroad where he might be ſeen of any; for that <hi>Stella</hi>'s Father having already given his word to the Count, ambitious of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing advanc'd to ſo honorable an Alliance, was ſo far from being to be appeas'd by any intreaty, or admitting of any of thoſe excuſes that were made by many of <hi>Carlo</hi>'s Friends in his behalf, that he complain'd to the Magiſtrate of the City, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd of him, to proclaim the reward of two thouſand Growns to whomſoever ſhould apprehend him, or bring any ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of him. This diligent inquiſition
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170098:40"/>did not at all trouble the minde of <hi>Cario,</hi> who thought himſelf ſecure in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-palace; nor did he care for going any whither abroad, having at home abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly enough to content him; for in the day time, beſide the company of his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, he entertain'd himſelf with the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of the Flowers, which yielded plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure both to his ſight and ſcent, and the ſoft Muſick of the cleer Streams: In the night-time he intermitted to be <hi>Stella</hi>'s Brother. And thus for a while they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd one another in ſecurity and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent delight.</p>
            <p>One evening they were ſitting together in the Garden, to take the benefit of the Weſt-winds cool whiſpers, when they might hear <hi>Lucinda</hi> (for ſo was the damoſel call'd, that was before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd) incited by the violence of Love, and ſecure of any bodies over-hearing her, breath forth her Paſſion in this Song.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>ON a green bank ſate a fair Shepherdeſs,</l>
                  <l>From whoſe Aſpect the morn might ſeem to riſe;</l>
                  <l>Save that ſome clouds of care and heavineſs,</l>
                  <l>Obſcur'd the ſerene luſtre of her eyes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:170098:41"/>Her ſighs into the empty Air ſhe vented;</l>
                  <l>She ſighing ſang, &amp; ſinging thus lamented:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How ſhall I ſhake this tyrant from my heart?</l>
                  <l>'Tis death alone, I fear, can Love remove:</l>
                  <l>If then my life be cauſe of all my ſmart,</l>
                  <l>Ceaſe heart to live, that I may ceaſe to love.</l>
                  <l>But if thou art deni'd by Fate to die,</l>
                  <l>This only's left, To ſuffer conſtantly.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucinda</hi> concluded her Song with ſo deep a ſigh, that <hi>Stella</hi> could not chuſe but obſerve it; and being touch'd with a kind of jealouſie, ſhe beheld <hi>Carlo</hi> with a look leſſe ſerene than at other times: but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he take any notice of it, nor ſeem'd ſhe at all to be troubled at it. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, in the infancy of their enjoyments, are ſcarce at leaſure to entertain jealouſie, or ſtrange Loves: yet <hi>Carlo</hi> his being ſo paſſionately lov'd by <hi>Lucinda,</hi> coſt him dear; for the Servant, whom <hi>Leonardo</hi> had appointed to attend upon the two Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, having, not many days ſince, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd a paſſion for <hi>Lucinda;</hi> and not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending any other cauſe of her inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, than that her heart was prepoſſeſt with an affection ſhe bore to <hi>Carlo,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought himſelf of a way either to ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170098:41"/>himſelf into her favour, or to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd of her for her diſdain, which was, to diſcover to her the whole progreſſe of the loves of thoſe two perſons, and the true reaſon of their living conceal'd in that place. As this action of his was moſt ignoble, to betray thoſe that were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his fidelity; ſo it far'd with him accordingly: he only obtaining the baleſt of thoſe ends which he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to himſelf: for this diſcovery did not at all move in <hi>Lucinda</hi> any affection for him, but only made her deſpair of that ſucceſſe which ſhe had promis'd to her ſelf in her love to <hi>Carlo,</hi> which was not long conceal'd from him himſelf.</p>
            <p>One day, as he was ſitting to repoſe himſelf at the foot of a ſhady tree, there appeared unto him, neer to the place where he ſate, <hi>Lucinda,</hi> in a poſture ſo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, that grief ſeem'd to have made her really, what was but feign'd of <hi>Niobe;</hi> which he ſtrictly obſerving, could not forbear to demand of her what might be the cauſe of her ſo deep melancholy? <q>The cauſe (reply'd ſhe, in a troubled and diſdainful way) is ſo apparent, that do but enquire of theſe trees, theſe flowers, nay, toeſe rocks themſelves, and they will all declare my ſufferings, being
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170098:42"/>much more ſenſible than thoſe that are the Authors of them. This purling foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that you ſee run whiſp'ring along the ſmooth pebbles, about what, think ye, are all her murmuring diſcourſes, but about my love, or rather my fondneſſe, who have ſuff'red my ſelf to be tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with an affection for him, who (by reaſon that he hath diſpos'd of his heart already to one that hath more right and title to it) is oblig'd to be inflexible to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward me? I know I ought not, as the caſe ſtands, to expect any milder treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from you but tell me plainly, ſince your true condition is not altogether hid from me, however you have ſought to mask it; Is not this <hi>Stella</hi> your Spouſe, whom you feign to be your Siſter? are not you Brother to Count <hi>Alfredo?</hi> and is not ſhe daughter to <hi>Don Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Aragon?</hi> did not you ſeduce her from her Fathers houſe? To what end ſerves this counterfeiting the names of Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Siſter, whenas the night, through all her darkneſſe, can diſcern a different relation? Little do you imagine into what inconveniences this diſguiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of yours hath plunged me: for had you appear'd at firſt what really you were, I had been ſufficiently warn'd to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170098:42"/>fortifie my minde againſt all unlawful deſires; it being a thing that cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into my thoughts, that any woman, be ſhe never ſo wanton or unchaſte, would give her ſelf liberty to cheriſh in her breaſt a paſſion for one who is intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anothers. But, Oh unhappy me that I am, not to be inform'd of your true condition, until I had loſt my ſelf and my liberty in a fond miſapprehenſion: now I am diſdeceiv'd, I ſhall labour with my whole might, to ſuppreſſe theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable flames, before they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed any farther to ruine me. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, I would not have you ignorant that you owe your ſafety to the good will which I have born you, though now I ſtrive to forget it: and do not imagine I ſpeak this to flatter you; for is there any one, think you, that knows the abode of a perſon whom Juſtice requires, and hearing the reward of two thouſand Crowns propos'd to whomſoever ſhould bring tydings of him, would have patience to conceal ſuch a perſon, without ſome great conſideration? You ſee I know your abode, and who you are; having an opportunity both to be rich, and to revenge my ſelf of your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain; if I did not approve the reaſon of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170098:43"/>it, and forgive it: but to give you proof how unfeignedly my affection hath been, and to let you ſee that I am not really what theſe homely garments make me appear to be, long may you enjoy your fair <hi>Stella</hi> with all the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity and happineſſe that theſe Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes can afford, while I implore Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to give me ſtrength to extinguiſh theſe flames which my breaſt hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately harbour'd ſo long: And I doubt not, but Time, which is wont to bring about greater miracles, will alſo effect this, ſince we oft-times ſee, that that which is doated on to day, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is forgotten.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carlo</hi> remain'd in a kind of ecſtaſie, to hear from <hi>Lucinda</hi>'s mouth ſuch an exact relation of the important accidents of his life; and was ſomwhat comforted in the aſſurances ſhe gave him of keeping ſecret all that ſhe knew of him: yet knowing how little confidence ought to be repos'd in one that loves without being beloved again; and that his own life, and the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Stella</hi> depended upon her ſilence; he thought it his wiſeſt courſe to appear out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to her, not altogether inſenſible of her love; ſuppoſing, that by a ſeeming compliance, though but for a while, ſhe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170098:43"/>might be lull'd into ſuch a pleaſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, as might make her forget all thoughts of divulging any thing to his harm: And juſt as he was putting this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution in practice, telling her how much her good eſteem of him had oblig'd him, and wiſhing himſelf in a Condition free enough to entertain her love; <hi>Stella,</hi> with whom it was an unwonted thing, to be never ſo little abſent from him, going to ſeek him in that fair province of Flowers, came to a little thicket of Myrtles and Laurels, through which, although ſhe could not ſee him; yet by the diſtinct ſound of his Speech, ſhe gheſs'd him to be but at a ſmall diſtance from her: her curioſity, to know who it was that he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd with, led her to a tree, whoſe branches wider diſplay'd than the reſt, permitted her plainly to diſcern <hi>Lucinda</hi> and him together.</p>
            <p>This unexpected ſight, inflam'd her with a deſire to know what ſhould be the occaſion of this ſo great familiarity; ſo that (with a moſt greedy attention) draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as neer as poſſibly ſhe could without being diſcern'd, ſhe heard <hi>Carlo</hi> ſay, (but it was rather to engage <hi>Lucinda</hi> to ſec acy, than out of any free inclination to ſerve her) <q>That he was no leſſe ſerſible of her
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170098:44"/>paſſion, than deeply affected with her beauty; and that if he did not requite her with thoſe real Services which her love deſerv'd from him, ſhe was to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it to a Cauſe that was very well known to her ſelf; for that being bound to <hi>Stella</hi> by obligations of ſo high a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the leaſt of them was her ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving left her Fathers houſe to follow him, he was utterly depriv'd of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to diſpoſe of himſelf according to his own minde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But that when his troubleſome eſtate ſhould be becalm'd, and his affairs quietly compos'd, he would contrive things ſo much to her contentment, that ſhe ſhould plainly ſee how much he was her Servant.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucinda</hi> upon this retir'd, perceiving ſome of the Gardiners people coming that way, not without reaſon; for her love was not ſo cloſely carried, but that it was whiſper'd among them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stella</hi> remain'd a while ſo loſt in aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, that ſhe had ſcarce life and ſence enough left in her, to perceive that ſhe was jealous; and when ſhe came to her ſelf, ſhe was not able to endure, ſo much as to think of <hi>Carlo</hi>'s treachery, or of <hi>Lucinda</hi>'s impudence: So tranſported ſhe was with rage and jealouſie, to ſee <hi>Carlo</hi> not only
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170098:44"/>love a perſon ſo much inferiour, but with ſo great a paſſion as to reveal thoſe things to her which he ought to have kept undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd, if it were poſſible, even from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; that ſhe ruſh'd out in a fury from among the buſhes, where ſhe had ſtood, exclaiming with loud and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d cries againſt his diſloyalty. <q>To what end, (ſaid ſhe) ingrateful man, ſerve all theſe feigned ſhews of affection, whenas I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently ſee that you only pretend a love to me, in the mean while carrying on a ſecret deſign, unworthy both of my qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, of your many obligations to me, and the dangers whereunto I have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd my ſelf for your ſake? you ought to appear what you are, <hi>Carlo,</hi> the moſt perfidious man the earth bears. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I ſhall not be able ſo far to forget the good eſteem I have formerly born you, as altogether to refrain from tears and pity, if your life ſhould chance to be indanger'd; yet this advantage I ſhould have, That I ſhould ſee my ſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd of the ignoble dealings of ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous a perſon; for it is much more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to a woman of a generous ſpirit, to die, than to bear the infidelity of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whom ſhe hath given her heart. How worthy a recompence have you gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170098:45"/>me for the loſſe of that which I held more dear than all things in the world beſide? Is it to this, that all thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are come, which flow'd from you in a ſtream of tears, when I permitted you to become maſter of this unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate beauty? I am glad, however, that at length you appear to me in your own co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours; that although I cannot take from you again, what to the prejudice of my honour you have already obtain'd of me, I may at leaſt free my ſelf from thoſe your impoſtures, to which hitherto I have liv'd a Victim: I am likely to ſee you ſhortly expos'd to the vengeance of your Brother and my Father, who as they are perſons both potent, and highly incens'd againſt you, will hardly be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with any thing leſs than your life: therefore I will only deal ſo candidly with you, as to give you warning before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, that you muſt look for no greater favour from me, than what you would expect from your greateſt enemy; and that I ſhall combine with thoſe that hate you, that they may proſecute you with the more violence.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Much more than this, had <hi>Stella</hi> to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if grief and vehement paſſion had not ſtop'd up the paſſage of her words: ſo ſhe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170098:45"/>retriv'd the violence of her grief with tears, which to a heart oppreſs'd with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive ſadneſſe, are rather a heart-eaſing, than a burthen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carlo</hi> obſerving the whole village rung of <hi>Stella</hi>'s loud Complaints, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering well the nature of thoſe ruſtick people, foreſaw that his Tragedy only wanted but little of being completed; aſſuring himſelf, that the news of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, would quickly be convey'd to thoſe that ſought his life; which was in effect no ſooner fear'd than accompliſh'd: For, one of the Bores, frantick with the hopes of Gold, flew to <hi>Sevil,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd the Miniſters of Juſtice of all that had paſs'd in the Village.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stella,</hi> in the mean time, was more than ever diſmay'd, when ſhe perceiv'd <hi>Carlo</hi> more ſenſible of her diſtaſte, than of the dangers that were impendent on him; and ſeeing him ſo much troubled and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger'd, ſhe could not chuſe but repent her of what ſhe had done.</p>
            <p>Love may well boaſt himſelf the Son of a God, ſince he partakes of quality ſo proper unto thoſe above, Aptneſſe to forgive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carlo,</hi> on the contrary, deſirous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170098:46"/>from <hi>Stella</hi>'s minde the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of Suſpition, brought <hi>Lucinda</hi> into her preſence, to manifeſt unto her the manner how ſhe came to be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with thoſe ſecrets which he had been ſuſpected to have declared unto her himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucinda</hi> having unfeignedly declar'd unto them the truth; <hi>Carlo,</hi> to make an end of cleering himſelf to <hi>Stella,</hi> told her,</p>
            <p>
               <q>That the reaſon why he ſpake ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligingly to one of her mean Condition, was, to engage her to be ſilent of what was in her power to divulge concerning them; conceiving it more prudence to delude her with falſe expectation, than to ſtand to the courteſie of an incenſed womans tongue, in matters of ſo great concernment.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stella</hi> confeſs'd her miſtake no otherwiſe than by ſilence; but within a very ſhort ſpace, while they were diſcourſing of the ſtrange accidents this night had produc'd, there came in a Meſſenger, to adviſe <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>That if he deſir'd not to come into the hands of Juſtice, it was then high time for him to make all poſſible ſpeed away, for that the Purſuivants were ſo
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170098:46"/>neer at hand, that it would be very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult for him, if not impoſſible, to eſcape them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stella</hi> alſo ſeeing the great danger he was like to incur, if they ſhould take him in her company, pray'd him to ſhift for himſelf, being that he was the principal object of her Fathers vengeance. He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly obey'd; and after ſome mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual careſſes, and many a deep fetch'd ſigh, took his leave; telling her, <q>That he would flye to <hi>Granada,</hi> where he had many Friends and Kindred, and there expect the blowing over of theſe ſtorms.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But to let him ſee how conſtant a friend his ill Fortune was to him, in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forſaking him; By that time he was arriv'd at the uttermoſt gate, he found his paſſage ſtopt up by his enemies; who demanding of him who he was? his high Courage would not conſent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them. Therefore drawing his Sword, he ſtood upon his own defence; thinking (as indeed he had reaſon) that alife would not be ill loſt, to avoid the miſeries of a priſon. And he had loſt it, if <hi>Leonardo</hi> had not come in opportunely enough to perſwade him, not to caſt away his life ſo raſhly, when he ſaw himſelf
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170098:47"/>over-power'd by ſo great a number of his purſuers: whereupon he rendred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, though with much regret, and more out of complyance with his Friends advice, than out of any fear of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies power. Having ſecured his perſon, they made a diligent ſearch after <hi>Stella;</hi> but that labour might well have been ſpar'd, for ſhe thinking <hi>Carlo</hi> had had time enough to evade the Hue and Cry that was made after him, thought it her beſt courſe likewiſe to commit her ſelf to the ſafeguard of her heels: and when the Souldiers were all buſied in apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Carlo,</hi> ſhe found a way to eſcape out at a contrary gate, which was not guarded; reſolving to take up her firſt ſtation at the very next Village ſhe came at.</p>
            <p>Thus, with a minde as calm as her Sorrows would permit, and the hopes that at length ſhe ſhould recover again the ſight of her dear <hi>Carlo,</hi> ſhe went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unattended by any other company ſave her own Sorrows, with whom ſhe ſilently diſcourſed all the way, till at length, overcome with wearineſſe, and invited by the freſhneſſe of a moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Rivolet that ran gently ſliding along under an impending Rock, ſhe caſt her
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170098:47"/>ſelf upon the Flowry bank, yielding up her Sences to the ſweet Captivity of Sleep, out of which her very cares could not waken her, until the Sun-beams gilded the mountain tops with light. When ſhe awak'd, and ſaw her ſelf alone, and in a ſtrange place; not knowing which way to direct her ſteps unto the place which ſhe intended, ſhe was in no ſmall perplexity: When caſting her eyes toward a pleaſant valley, ſhe ſaw a great flock of Sheep; and not far off, their Shepherd ſitting in a melancholy poſture; who to a certain muſical Inſtrument, which Shepherds uſe in thoſe Countries, ſung this following Sonnet:</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>CElio</hi> remains diſconſolate,</l>
                  <l>for ſaken of his cruel Lover;</l>
                  <l>Who not aſham'd to viclate</l>
                  <l>her Faith, doth her falſe heart diſcover.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oft doth he his hard Fate bemoan,</l>
                  <l>Inveighs on her inconſtant minde;</l>
                  <l>Oft blames himſelf, for deating on</l>
                  <l>A thing more fickle than the wind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Somtimes (unhappy man) he deem'd</l>
                  <l>Her abſence might have quench'd his flame;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170098:48"/>But now more fair than ere, ſhe ſeem'd;</l>
                  <l>His flames encreaſe through her diſdain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now nought is leſe him but deſpair:</l>
                  <l>His adverſe Fate brought him to ſee,</l>
                  <l>Things diſtant moſt admired are;</l>
                  <l>Enjoyment breeds ſatiety.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He goes to ſee the fair unkinde,</l>
                  <l>Whom her new Lovers arms immure;</l>
                  <l>Him ſhe vouchſaf'd not unce to minde,</l>
                  <l>In her incenſtancy ſecure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Was't not enough, <hi>Phyllis</hi> ſaid he,</l>
                  <l>That thy deceitful charming Wiles</l>
                  <l>Should cheat my fond credulity,</l>
                  <l>That thou ſeen'st others to beguile?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If amid'ſt theſe thy nere delights,</l>
                  <l>Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> haſt no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> me,</l>
                  <l>Think how awaken'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> frights;</l>
                  <l>Think <hi>Phyllis</hi> on thy perjury.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Longer to grieve he ſav 'twas vain,</l>
                  <l>Longer his troubled thoughts to vex;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Phyllis</hi> triumphs in her diſdain,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Phyllis</hi> the falſeſt of her ſeis.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>As ſoon as he had ended his Song, ſhe enquir'd of him, which was the way to the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170098:48"/>next Town? The Shepherd no ſooner ſaw her, but that by her ſurprizing beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and thoſe many graces that always accompanied her, his natural ruſticity was on a ſudden transform'd into thoſe Civilities, which might have befitted a perſonage of far higher rank; for beſides that he omitted no importunities to make her accept part of thoſe poor Viands which he carried in his Wallet; He left his flock, to conduct her to a little Village at the foot of a Mountain, where having provided her of a fit receptacle, both for Safety and Accommodation, he took his leave, and committed her to Heaven's protection.</p>
            <p>She remain'd not long in this Village, but remembring that <hi>Carlo</hi> had determin'd to go to <hi>Granada,</hi> ſhe prepar'd to go thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after him with all the ſpeed ſhe could: to that end, ſhe ſold one of her Jewels, and furniſh'd her ſelf with a Mule, and other neceſſaries for her Journey; and hir'd a poor labouring man to be her guide; who promis'd to ſerve her with all faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>But before ſhe arriv'd at <hi>Granada, Carlo</hi> was a cloſe Priſoner in <hi>Sevil,</hi> and under ſtrict guard: but ſo many, and ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful were his friends, and ſo great the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170098:49"/>the whole City bare him for his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny laudable qualities, that <hi>Don Fernando,</hi> mollified by their perſwaſions, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to pardon all that was paſt, ſo that his Daughter were but reſtor'd him. They diſpach'd Meſſengers in all haſte to the Village where <hi>Carlo</hi> and ſhe had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd; but the people Certified them, That ſhe ſtole away from thence the ſame night that <hi>Carlo</hi> was apprehended: Then they made a ſtrict enquiry through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all <hi>Sevil,</hi> but could not meet with any body that could give them the leaſt inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation where ſhe was.</p>
            <p>This was a grief which went deepeſt to <hi>Carlo</hi>'s heart of all that had yet befaln; wherefore he beſought Heaven with tears, to fortifie him with patience againſt all the heavie Croſſes that crouded ſo faſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alfredo</hi> now is he only, of all men, who grieves not that ſhe is loſt; who ſince he had been ſo unſuccesful in his Love to her, is become ſo far poſſeſs'd with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt her, that he wiſh'd in his heart no leſſe miſchief were befallen her, than the loſſe of her life. But his evil wiſhes recoil'd upon his own head, inſtead of reaching her to whoſe harm they were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected: For <hi>Stella</hi> had not been long ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170098:49"/>at <hi>Granada,</hi> before ſhe received infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of <hi>Carlo</hi>'s impriſonment, and of her Fathers indulgence to her: ſhe ſpeeded away a Meſſenger to Certifie him that ſhe was in <hi>Granada,</hi> and in health. The Old man over-joy'd to hear ſuch welcome News, went forth to receive her, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with <hi>Carlo,</hi> and the prime Gentry of the City: Only <hi>Alfredo</hi> refus'd to contribute his preſence to that Feſtivity, wherein others joy was his diſcomfort; nay, ſo ſenſible was he of his reproach, when he perceiv'd that his envie and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble carriage was notorious to the world, that ſoon after, he kept his Chamber; and being ſeiz'd with a violent ſickneſſe ariſing from no other apparent Cauſe but a deep melancholy, within a few weeks he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his wretched days.</p>
            <p>The Sorrow which <hi>Carlo</hi> had for his Brothers death, was greater then might have been expected from him who gain'd ſo fair an inheritance by it, and who had been ſo diſcourteonſly treated by him in his life-time: But Nature commonly combines more effectually, than other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects can diſ-unite; eſpecially in noble breaſts, and thoſe not poſſeſs'd with the Spirit of Ambition. With a ſerene and ſober countenance, he receiv'd the congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulations
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170098:50"/>of his new Eſtate, and gave God thanks that had freed him from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of miſery, and brought him to a tranquillity of life, which but a few days before he deſpair'd of ever obtaining: (ſo it moſt frequently falls out, that good or bad Fortune come when they are leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.) Thus, after many rugged brunts of adverſity, <hi>Carlo</hi> liv'd in great Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and happineſſe, enjoying the ſociety of his beloved <hi>Stella,</hi> and the Honours of his deceaſed Brother, of whom the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon voyce was, That Rancor and Envie ſhortned his life: a deſerved End for him that repines at other mens Proſperities, as if they were his own Afflictions.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170098:50"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> Theſe Books following, are Printed by <hi>Nath. Brook,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>Times Treaſury or Academy for the Gentry, for their accompliſhment in Arguments of diſcourſe, habit, faſhion: ſummed up all in a Character of Honour, by <hi>Ri. Brathwait</hi> Eſq.</item>
               <item>That excellent piece of Phyſiognomy and Chiromancy, Metopoſcopy, the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrical Proportions and Signal Moles of the body; the ſubject of Dreams: to which is added, The Art of Memory. By <hi>Ri. Sanders.</hi> Fol.</item>
               <item>Magick Aſtrology vindicated, by <hi>H. Warren.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fons Lacrymarum:</hi> or, a Fountain of Tears, with an Elegy upon Sir <hi>Charls Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas.</hi> By <hi>J Quarles.</hi> 8.</item>
               <item>A treatile of Contentation, fit for theſe ſad and troubleſom times. By <hi>Joſ. Hall,</hi> late B. of <hi>Exon</hi> and <hi>Norwich.</hi> 12</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170098:51"/>Mirrour of Complements, fitted for Ladies, Gentlewomen, Scholars, and Strangers; with forms of ſpeaking and writing of Letters moſt in faſhion: with witty Poems, and a Table expoun ding hard Engliſh words.</item>
               <item>Divinity no enemy to Aſtrology: A Sermon for the Society of Aſtrologers for the year 1653. By Dr. <hi>Tho. Swadlin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Select Thoughts: or, Choice Helps for a pious Spirit, beholding the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of her Lord Jeſus, by <hi>J. Hall,</hi> B. of <hi>Norwich.</hi> A new piece.</item>
               <item>The holy Order, or Fraternity of Mourners in <hi>Zion.</hi> To which is added Songs in the night: or, Chearfulneſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Affliction, by <hi>Joſ. Hall,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich.</hi> A new piece.</item>
               <item>The Art of Memory: a cure for a weak Memory, uſeful to all perſons, from the Gown to the Clown. A new piece.</item>
               <item>That complete piece called the Exact Surveyor of Land, ſhewing how to plot all manner of Grounds, and to reduce and divide the ſame. Alſo Iriſh meaſure, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to Engliſh ſtatute Meaſure; uſeful for all that either ſell or purchaſe, by <hi>I. E.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Milk for Children: or, A plain and eaſie Method teaching to <hi>Read</hi> and to <hi>Write,</hi> with brief Rules for School-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb facs="tcp:170098:51"/>to inſtruct their Scholars in, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to inſtruct their Families in, by Dr. <hi>Thomas.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Culpepers</hi> Phyſical and Chyrurgical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, of his own admired Experience, never publiſhed before now by his Wife, being his laſt Legacies.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Culpepers Semiotica:</hi> or, his Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Judgment of Diſeaſes, much enlarged from the Decumbiture of the ſick, which way to finde out the Cauſe, Change, and End of the Diſeaſe. Alſo whether the ſick be likely to live or die: With the ſigns of life and death by the body of the fick party, according to the Judgment of <hi>Hippocrates.</hi> With a Treatiſe of Urines, by <hi>N. Culpeper.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi> his fourth Book of <hi>Occult</hi> Philoſophy, of <hi>Geomancy:</hi> Magical Elements of <hi>Peter de Abano,</hi> the nature of Spirits, made Engliſh by <hi>R. Turner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pulpit Sparks, being ſet forms of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers uſed before Sermon by Dr. <hi>Jeremiah Taylor,</hi> Dr. <hi>Cillingham,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hewit,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Eminent Divines.</item>
               <item>The Queens Cloſet opened. Incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſecrets in Phyſick, Chyrurgery; preſerving, candying, and cooking, as they were preſented to the Queen, tranſcribed from the true Copies of her Majeſties own
<pb facs="tcp:170098:52"/>receipt-Books by <hi>W. M.</hi> one of her late Servants.</item>
               <item>The Conveyancers Light, or the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete Clark and Scrivener's Guide, being an Exact draught of all Preſidents and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances now in uſe, as they were penned and perfected by divers Learned Judges, eminent Lawyers, and great Conveyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, both antient and modern; whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is added a Concordance from <hi>K. Rich.</hi> 3. to this preſent.</item>
               <item>Wits Interpreter, the Engliſh <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> or a ſure Guide to thoſe admirable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments, that complete our Engliſh Gentry in the moſt acceptable qualificari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Diſcourſe or Writing: Alſo the whole Myſtery of thoſe pleaſing Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts of Eloquence and Love are made eaſe, in the Art of Reaſoning, Theatre of Courtſhip, Labyrinth of Fancies, Love-Songs, Drollery; The perfect Inditer of Letters, <hi>Alamode,</hi> by <hi>I. C.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Floating Iſland, a Tragedy-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy acted before the King, by the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of <hi>Chriſt-Church.</hi> By Dr. <hi>Stroud.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wit and Drollery: with other Jovial Poems.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paracelſus</hi> of Occult Philoſophy, or his Secrets of Nature.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:170098:52"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
